<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God's mighty power magnified as manifested and revealed in his faithful handmaid Joan Vokins, who departed this life the 22d of the 5th month, 1690, having finished her course, and kept the faith : also some account of her exercises, works of faith, labour of love, and great travels in the work of the ministry, for the good of souls.</title>
            <author>Vokins, Joan, d. 1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9069</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12147085</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12147085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 902:45)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God's mighty power magnified as manifested and revealed in his faithful handmaid Joan Vokins, who departed this life the 22d of the 5th month, 1690, having finished her course, and kept the faith : also some account of her exercises, works of faith, labour of love, and great travels in the work of the ministry, for the good of souls.</title>
                  <author>Vokins, Joan, d. 1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 130, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Northcott ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vokins, Joan, d. 1690.</term>
               <term>Christian biography.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:1"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>God's Mighty Power Magnified:</hi> AS MANIFESTED and REVEALED IN HIS Faithful Handmaid JOAN VOKINS, WHO Departed this Life the 22d of the 5th Month, 1690, <hi>Having finiſhed her Courſe, and kept the Faith.</hi> Alſo ſome Account of her Exerciſes, Works of Faith, Labour of Love, and great Travels in the Work of the Miniſtry, for the good of Souls.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Cor. 4. 7.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we have this Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, that the Excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Cor. 12. 9.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he ſaid, my Grace is ſufficient for thee for my Strength is made perfect in Weakneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Northcott,</hi> in <hi>George-Yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following Papers and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles here Collected together, and Printed for thy benefit, were not written and given forth by the Will of Man, or worldly Wiſdom, but by the Will and hidden Wiſdom of God, which is (and ever was) a Myſtery to the Learned <hi>Scribes,</hi> and wiſe Diſputants of this World, and as Fooliſhneſs to them.</p>
            <p>Therefore if thou wouldſt come to receive the comfort that is couched under the Words and Expreſſions, and partake of the Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Life from whence they proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then thou muſt turn in thy Mind to the Manifeſtation of the Spirit of Chriſt, which doth enlighten thee and all Mankind, and is in great Mercy freely given thee to profit
<pb facs="tcp:54975:3"/> withal, which Gift of God is the only Key that opens the Myſteries of Life and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reveals the things of God; which no Man can know or underſtand, but by the Inſpiration of that ſame Holy Spirit, which I deſire thou maiſt in Humility wait to feel, to open and enlarge thy Heart, by inſpiring thee, and thereby a good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding maiſt obtain, both to diſcern the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to thy Peace, and alſo to ſavour and taſte thereof, to thy Comfort and Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſo to have the Senſe from the Witneſs in thy own Conſcience, from whence the following things came.</p>
            <p>So requeſting thee to read without Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, in the fear of that God that ſearcheth thy Heart, that thou maiſt receive the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which in true Love is heartily wiſhed thee, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Sincere Friend, <hi>O. SANSOM</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note_to_the_reader">
            <p>Note, That the following Papers are not exactly placed, as to the Dates, which the Reader is deſired to paſs by.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Account and Teſtimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning</hi> Joan Vokins, <hi>from the Quarterly Meeting for</hi> Berkſhire.</head>
            <p>AS concerning our Dear Friend and well-beloved Siſter in the Lord, <hi>Joan Vokins,</hi> this Account and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony Lives in our Hearts to give forth, That ſhe was one whom the Lord Called by his Grace, and Endued with Power from on High, to Preach the Goſpel of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and (according to her Meaſure) her Labour and Exerciſe therein was Effectual to many; and her Care and Diligence in her Service very Uſeful and Profitable in the Churches of Chriſt, where ſhe hath Travelled, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in thoſe parts where her Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb facs="tcp:54975:4"/> was. She was given up to Serve the Lord with her whole Might, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on the Sufficiency of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and did not count her Life, nor any thing of this World dear unto unto her, for the Works ſake which the Lord had called her unto; but with great Courage and Confidence, truſting in him, (who was her ſole ſupport) ſhe chearfully expoſed her weak Body to Travel, enduring great Hardſhips both by Sea and Land, in the Work and Service of the Lord, when many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils and Dangers divers ways did attend her; and tho outwardly Weak, ſhe was made Strong through Believing in God's Almighty Power. And now having Fought a good Fight, and Finiſhed her Courſe here with Joy, and laid down her Head in peace; ſhe is Crowned with endleſs Life and Glory to Sing Praiſes and Hallelujah's to the Lord for ever and evermore. And through her Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God in her day, and Valour for his Truth, and Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy unto the End, ſhe hath obtained a good Report among all God's People
<pb facs="tcp:54975:4"/> (that knew her) in her Generation: Her Converſation did Adorn her Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Profeſſion, and was ſuch as did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Goſpel; ſo that ſhe Practiſed what ſhe Preached, and was a Lively Pattern and good Example unto others in her day.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing there are few that are in all things like-minded, then ſurely the loſs of ſuch a Member in the Churches is great, and her Work and Service wanted and miſſed much among us: But ſeeing it is her great Gain that ſhe is ceaſed from her Labours, and our God's good pleaſure to Receive her into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Reſt; It is our Duty humbly to ſubmit, and ſay, <hi>Thy will, O God, be done. And, O Lord, do thou by thy own Power raiſe up more ſuch Faithful Labourers, and ſuch Nurſing Mothers in thy</hi> Iſrael, <hi>as this was,</hi> which thou haſt now removed.</p>
            <p>So for the Glorifying of our God, and Magnifying of his Life and Power, which through Chriſt Jeſus, was Revealed and Manifeſted in this our dear Friend and Siſter in the Truth aforeſaid, we were free to give forth this ſhort Account and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony with our Names Subſcribed.</p>
            <closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:54975:5"/>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Signed at the Quarterly Meeting at</hi> Reading,
<date>
                     <hi>the 4th of the</hi> 3<hi>d Month,</hi> 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Paul Newman.</item>
                     <item>William Auſtell.</item>
                     <item>John Gidden.</item>
                     <item>William Cooper.</item>
                     <item>Oliver Sanſom.</item>
                     <item>William Speakman.</item>
                     <item>Adam Lawrence.</item>
                     <item>John Knowles.</item>
                     <item>John May.</item>
                     <item>William Lambole.</item>
                     <item>James Potter.</item>
                     <item>Edw. Lockey.</item>
                     <item>James Mathew.</item>
                     <item>John Jagger.</item>
                     <item>John Buy.</item>
                     <item>John Cotterell.</item>
                     <item>Abraham Bonifeild.</item>
                     <item>John Brown.</item>
                     <item>William Ballard.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>The above-ſaid Teſtimony being Read at the Womans Half years Meeting for the ſaid County, held at</hi> Reading, <hi>on the ſelf ſame day above Specified, and in Witneſs of their Unity with their Brethren therein, and truly owning the ſame, did alſo ſet their Hands as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Martha Weſton.</item>
                  <item>Jane Tull.</item>
                  <item>Grace Hutchings.</item>
                  <item>Mary Sandilans.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54975:5"/>
                  <item> Marjery Potter.</item>
                  <item>Elizabeth Addams.</item>
                  <item>Marab. Farmborrow.</item>
                  <item>Mary Baker.</item>
                  <item>Mary Buy.</item>
                  <item>Margaret Chandler.</item>
                  <item>Damaris Burgis.</item>
                  <item>Mary Auſtell.</item>
                  <item>Deborah Mathew.</item>
                  <item>Joan Orpwood.</item>
                  <item>Rachel Nicholls.</item>
                  <item>Mary Cooper.</item>
                  <item>Jane Ballard.</item>
                  <item>Mary Cotterell.</item>
                  <item>Marjery Bunce.</item>
                  <item>Alice Glover.</item>
                  <item>Jane Sanſom.</item>
                  <item>Elizab. Wightwick.</item>
                  <item>Elizabeth Bullock.</item>
                  <item>Ann Ball.</item>
                  <item>Mary Brown.</item>
                  <item>Ann Truſs.</item>
                  <item>Frances Wren.</item>
                  <item>Margret Fulbrook.</item>
               </list>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Teſtimony concerning</hi> Joan Vokins, <hi>by</hi> Theophila Townſend.</head>
            <p>I Have a Teſtimony in my Heart to bear for that faithfull Servant and Hand-Maid of the Lord, <hi>Joan Vokins;</hi> That ſhe was a vertuous Woman, truly fearing God, and one that was full of Zeal and Courage in her Teſtimony for the Lord, and his bleſſed Truth in her Day and Time, and did the Work of the Lord with boldneſs, and holy Confidence, and much Chearfulneſs: She ſtood a Witneſs for the Truth in faithfulneſs, unto the end of her days, againſt all that did riſe up in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſought to hinder the Proſperity of it where ſhe was concerned. I have known her above twenty years, and have had a Correſpondency with her by Letters, and have been at her Houſe, and ſhe hath been often with me, whereby I had the knowledge of her
<pb facs="tcp:54975:6"/> Affairs relating to the precious Truth, and of her godly Care and Diligence in the work of the Lord. She was of a tender Spirit, ready to hold forth a Hand to the weak, to help them on in the way of Peace, and to watch over them for good, and encourage them in well-doing; and much delighted to ſee thoſe that knew the Truth, grow up into the Life and Nature of it, to perſevere in it in faithfulneſs, but much lamenting the ſtate of the unfaithful. She had a godly care upon her for the Church of Chriſt in general, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where ſhe had laboured, and been converſant. Her tender Care was great; She was a Nurſing Mother over the Young convinced; and in her own Family, great was her Care and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for her Husband and Children, that they might partake with her of the Everlaſting Comfort, and Celeſtial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation that is the Portion of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. The Lord was very good unto her, and bleſſed her with a Diſpenſation of the Goſpel, and gave her a Word in ſeaſon to ſpeak to their ſeveral ſtates
<pb facs="tcp:54975:7"/> and conditions; and the Lord bleſſed her Endeavours, and made it effectual for their Benefit, and her great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Satisfaction: For ſhe was a great Sufferer in the time of her firſt Convincement among her near Relations. And ſhe was a good Example among them, that by her good Converſation, by the bleſſing of God, and aſſiſtance of his Grace they were won to the Truth; her care was great for her Children, that they might come to a ſenſe of Truth; that (ſhe ſaid) when ſhe ſaw them cumbered, and their Minds hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with their worldly Buſineſs, that ſhe would call them together to ſit down and wait upon the Lord, and ſit with them, that he might compoſe their Minds into an inward Retiredneſs, and ſaid, the Lord was with her in it, and often refreſhed her Spirit among them: And the Lord let her live to ſee the Fruits of her labour, and the deſire of her Soul concerning them, and the good effect that her Chriſtian Motherly care had brought forth, through the bleſſing of Almighty God, among them; to him
<pb facs="tcp:54975:7"/> be the Glory, for he is worthy for ever.</p>
            <p>Her Father, and Husband, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, all came to receive the Truth; and her Husband is now a Sufferer for Truth, under that cruel Oppreſſion of Tythes, a Priſoner at <hi>Reading-Goal,</hi> with her eldeſt Son for the ſame: And when they were called to ſuffer, ſhe ſignified to me in a Letter, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced her Heart to ſee them willing to ſuffer in ſo good a Cauſe. And her zeal and fervency for the holy Truth was ſuch, that ſhe rejoyced to ſee her near and dear Relations ſuffer for it; not that ſhe was glad becauſe they were Sufferers, but becauſe they were faithful to the Lord, and did chuſe rather to ſuffer than deny their Teſtimony againſt Tythes, that Antichriſtian Yoke, which the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion groans under, the weight of which, the Lord will overturn in his own ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and eaſe his own Heritage of that heavy Burden; for he is a never-failing God to his faithful People. Theſe things are not written only for her ſake that is taken from us, but alſo for the ſakes of them that remain in the Body,
<pb facs="tcp:54975:8"/> that they may be like-minded with her, and be found in the ſame Practice, watching againſt evil in their Children and Families, and encouraging them in a holy Life, and judge down Pride and Vanity, and all Superfluity, and every hurtful thing, that they may receive the ſame Bleſſing, and ſweet Satisfaction from the Lord, as this our dear De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Friend and Siſter did, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of her Soul, and renewing of her Zeal and Courage in the Work and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Lord; who in the Power of God, went on to ſerve the Lord with all her Might, offering up all that was near and dear unto her, not ſparing her weak Body, which in appearance, was fitter to keep her Chamber, than travel as ſhe did; who left Husband and Children, and all outward Enjoyments for the Truth ſake, and went over-Sea to anſwer the Lord, and clear herſelf of the Service he had called her unto; and he was with her, and did ſupport and uphold her by his mighty Power, and made way for her to travel through ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Iſlands and Provinces, as may be
<pb facs="tcp:54975:8"/> ſeen more at large in the following ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>She came to viſit me not long before ſhe went laſt up to <hi>London,</hi> and told me ſhe had ſome Papers ſhe deſired might be made publick after her Deceaſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting her time was not long to remain in the Body, being well ſatisfied, that ſhe ſhould lay down her Head in Peace with God, let Death come when it would. Her Trials and Exerciſes were many, but that which was her greateſt Grief, and heavieſt Burden, and moſt grievous to be born, was her ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by falſe Brethren and Apoſtates, who under the form and profeſſion of Truth, did make War, and kick againſt the Life and Power of it; but her Zeal for God, was againſt that Libertine back-ſliding Spirit: And the Lord bore up her Head, and ſupported her at all times, and brought her through it all, and now hath taken her to himſelf out of all their reach, where <hi>She reſts from her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and her works do follow her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in her laſt Letter, dated <hi>London</hi> in the 4th Month, 1690. ſhe ſignified,
<pb facs="tcp:54975:9"/> now her Service was finiſhed, and ſaid, I could gladly have laid down my Body here among the Lord's Worthies; yet ſeeing it is otherwiſe ordered, I ſubmit to the Will of my God, and do think to go Homeward in a little time, or to this purpoſe, as if ſhe had known her time to be near at Hand; and it was very near indeed, for ſhe did not reach Home, but dyed at <hi>Reading</hi> in Peace with the Lord, and in Unity with all his faithful People: And bleſſed be the worthy Name of the Lord, ſhe is now ſet free from all Sorrow, Pain and Weakneſs of Body, ſhe was attended with.</p>
            <p>And now the Lord hath taken her to her Everlaſting Reſt, out of all Trials, and her Peace is ſure, and her Reſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: Holy high Praiſes to the God of all our Mercies and Bleſſings, who knows beſt what to do with us, and in what ſeaſon to take us out of the World, and when it will be moſt for his Glory and our Good: Although we feel the want of her, and bewail our loſs, yet our loſs is her great Gain; She was
<pb facs="tcp:54975:9"/> very ſerviceable in the Country where ſhe lived, and elſewher; they miſs her, and we; all that were acquainted with her, know the want of her, yet can ſay in ſubmiſſion to the Will of God, <hi>Thy Will be done, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is what was with me in a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for my dear Deceaſed Friend and Siſter in the Truth, <hi>J. V.</hi> with whom my Spirit had true Unity: And though her Body is removed, yet her Life is with us.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cirenceſter,</hi>
                  <date>the 10th day of the 2d. Month, 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Theophila Townſend.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:10"/>
            <head>Mary Drewet's <hi>Testimony Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning</hi> Joan Vokins.</head>
            <p>COncerning our dear and well-belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Friend and Siſter, <hi>Joan Vokins,</hi> who was ſomtimes Converſant with us, and when it pleaſed the Lord to order her way to Viſit us, it was very Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and Edifying to the Sincere Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Loved the Truth: Her Innocent Life and Converſation lives in our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and the ſenſe of the Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kindneſs of the Lord is worthy to be retained and kept in mind by all his People, which was largely and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly manifeſted in preſerving and uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her, through many and great Exerciſes and Tryals, in her Service and Travels in the Work of the Lord, even when great Pains and Weakneſſes of Body were upon her, which did very much attend her all along ſince (and ſometime before) the Lord was pleaſed to call her forth in his Service; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born up by his Spirit, ſhe was given
<pb facs="tcp:54975:10"/> up in his Will, to be at his Diſpoſe, and did not look at her own Weakneſs, but was preſerved in the true Patience, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Faith ſtanding in the Bleſſed Power of the Lord, that failed not; her Afflictions being Rightly Sanctified unto her, ſo that ſhe was made able, tho in many Pains and Weakneſſes of Body, to undergo and perform the Service the Lord called her unto with Chearfulneſs; and it was her Joy to ſee Friends proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the Truth; and altho her bodily Preſence and Speech did ſeem Weak, yet her Teſtimony and Writing was Weighty and Powerful; for the Lord in the riches of his Love had made her a partaker of Heavenly Treaſure in her Earthen Veſſel, which I have heard her often acknowledg, taking nothing to her ſelf, but Aſcribed the Glory and Excellency of the Power, to be the free Gift of God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. Her care was great concerning the young Generation, Exhorting them to be inwardly ſtaid in their Minds, that they might grow up in the Love and Life of Truth, ſo as to feel the work of
<pb facs="tcp:54975:11"/> it effected in their own Hearts, that they might come up to ſerve the Lord and ſucceed their Heavenly minded Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who had finiſhed their Courſe, and weare at Reſt in the Lord. And ſo now ſeeing it hath pleaſed the Lord to take unto himſelf this our dear Friend, who hath done the work of her day in Faithfulneſs, and is entred into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſt and Peace with the Lord, to Sing praiſe and Hallelujah's to his Holy Name for ever and for ever more: So de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that we who are left a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, may prize our time ſo, as to walk in the Foot-ſteps of the Faithful that are gone before, who have ſought a City as Faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> did, whoſe Builder and Maker is the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cirencester,</hi>
                  <date>the 11th of the 2d Month. 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Mary Drewet.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Concerning our Dear and Tender Mother,</hi> Joan Vokins, <hi>who departed this Life the</hi> 22<hi>d of the 5th Month,</hi> 1690. <hi>at</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>in the County of</hi> Berks, <hi>at our Friend</hi> John Buy<hi>'s Houſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SHE being come from <hi>London</hi> homewards, it pleaſed the Lord to put a ſtop to her Journey, and take her to himſelf out of all Troubles, and from her many ſore Pains, which her poor Body was afflicted with. She was one that did truly fear the Lord, and ſought the Proſperity of his precious Truth above all the Glory and Honour of this World. Whenſoever the Lord was pleaſed to ſend her forth in his Service, ſhe went with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out murmuring, believing the Lord would carry her through it, though weak in Body; who did enable her to bear a faithful Living Teſtimony to his Name, in this her Native Land, and in places remote beyond the Seas, as in <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and in other parts of <hi>America,</hi> and in <hi>Ireland,</hi> through great Exerciſes, in Patience and Chearfulneſs, it being as Meat and Drink to her to do his Will. She was one that had a great Care in her Family of us her Children, that we might be <hi>nurtur'd, and brought up in the Fear of the Lord,</hi> and have a true Regard unto him, and his precious Truth, above all things in this World. This
<pb facs="tcp:54975:12"/> was her earneſt Deſire and Prayer to the Lord for us, That <hi>we might be his Children, that ſo we might truly anſwer the End for which we were created.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, though we cannot but ſorrow for the loſs of ſo near and dear a Mother as ſhe was to us, both inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, in giving us good Counſel, to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification, from our Childhood; But ſince it hath pleaſed the Lord to take her to himſelf; and conſidering, ſhe hath laid down her Head in the Faith, and full Aſſurance of Eternal Happineſs, it doth out-ballance all; ſhe having <hi>ceaſed from her Labours, is at reſt with the Lord,</hi> who is worthy of Praiſes and Honour for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Vokins,</hi> jun.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hopeful Vokins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Samuel Burgis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Elizabeth Vokins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mary Lockey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sarah Lawrence.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hannah Burgis.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Account given by</hi> Richard Vokins, junior, <hi>of ſome Words that his dear Mother ſpoke to him on her Dying Bed,</hi> Viz.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SON,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Weakneſs is great, and my Pains very ſtrong; but the Lord is large in his Love to me, and good to me; he gives me Patience to bear my Pains, which are ſtrong.</p>
            <p>Ah, Son! I have learned a good Leſſon, <hi>Paul</hi>'s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Leſſon, <hi>in all States to be content:</hi> and now I have nothing to do but to die. <hi>So putting forth her Hand, to take her Leave of me, further ſaid:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Son, Remember the Lord, and he will remember thee: And remember my Love to thy Wife, and to all my Children. <hi>And after a little ſtop, being weak, and her Speech low, ſpoke theſe Words again:</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord, and he will remember you; and be you faithful to him, and he will bleſs you, and you ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Vokins.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>This is my Teſtimony concerning my dear Siſter,</hi> Joan Vokins.</head>
            <p>SHE was a True and Faithful Labourer in the Churches of God, where it was her Care, that all Things might be kept Sweet and Clean, Decent and in Order, as becomes the Bleſſed Truth; ſhe having <hi>choſen the One thing needful, which is the better part, that ſhall never be taken away;</hi> and being given up to follow the Lord faithfully in his Work and Service; Her Prayer often in Publick was, That the Lord would ſubdue Death and Darkneſs out of our Meetings and Families; and we might come to witneſs him to be a Fountain of Life unto us. She was very tender-hearted, kind, and Loving, willing to do good unto all, and hath left a good Savour behind her; who <hi>though dead, yet liveth.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Daniel Bunce.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54975:14"/>
            <head>An Epistle to Friends writ firſt of all which came to hand, after the fore going was thus collected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</head>
            <p>UPON the Third Day of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Month, 1669, as I lay very ſick in my Bed, I felt the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting bleſſed powerful Life to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and ſpring up in my Heart, which gave Dominion over my bodily weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and cauſed me to write theſe few Lines unto you, that ſo we may conſider the large Love of our God, and praiſe his holy Name together.</p>
            <p>Dear Friends, the tender Bowels of God's Love dearly yearns towards you all; and in his Light hath he made it manifeſt: therefore it greatly concerns you all with the pure Light to make diligent ſearch into the very bottom of your Hearts, whether or no ye be faithful to what is manifeſt therein: for I write unto you as unto them that know the Truth, to ſtir you up to Faithfulneſs therein,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54975:15"/> that the Father's drawings ye may more and more feel, and through it come to Living O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, while the Bowels of tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are open; for if you ſlight his Loving-Kindneſs unto you, is it not juſt with him to ſhut up his Bowels of Compaſſion? Oh how largely hath the pure God of Heaven and Earth manifeſted his Loving-Kindneſs unto you! through his Judgments and Mercies, and through the Reproofs of his Inſtructions hath the way of Life been manifeſted largely unto you. Therefore, dear Friends, be not forgetful of his large Love: Oh, let it never ſlip out of your remembrance; for you can never prize it to the worth of it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it concerns you all to be truly watchful the remainder of your Days, that ſo you may ſee the appearances of his Love, and with your whole Hearts joyn thereunto, that no Reſerve may be left therein to ſtop the Current of the pure Life from flowing into your Souls: And, dear Hearts, it's in my Heart to ſtir you up to feel after the pure Life, if haply you may find it: Whilſt the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is open, be ye not negligent, nor unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; but be faithful and obedient, that ſo through the Faith that purifies the Heart, you may draw Water at the Fountain of Life, and feel its recourſe into your Souls; the Vertue whereof makes the Souls of the obedient fruitful and encreaſing in God's Love, and in their Unity with each other. But where the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54975:15"/> Current is ſtopped, and the Life hath not its free courſe, there Death is over the Soul, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs what they will; yea, though they may live in the very Form of Truth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, dear Friends, I, in God's Fear, and in the Bowels of tender Love to your Immortal Souls, do exhort you all to be diligent, to keep your Meetings, and aſſemble your ſelves often together; let not the gain of the periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things hinder you of the gain of that which will never periſh; For verily there's none can witneſs a free recourſe unto the Fountain of Life, but thoſe whoſe Hearts are gathered out of the periſhing things; and ſuch do partake of the living Springs, which do greatly refreſh their immortal Souls; and it's more to me than I can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. Therefore, dear Hearts, think not your time long, neither let the World hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but keep your Meetings frequently, there to wait with ſincere Hearts; for thoſe that ſo wait, never loſe their Reward; therefore be ye encouraged to wait upon the Lord, that in the pure refreſhing Life your Souls may come to have an Habitation, the which to know a dwelling and abiding in, is more precious than words can demonſtrate: And let Patience have its perfect Work in your Hearts, that all Prejudice may be kept out; for where Envy and Strife is, there is Confuſion. Therefore, dear Friends, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you all to dwell in the Patience, and in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54975:16"/> the Wiſdom that comes from above, which is firſt <hi>pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, without Partiality, and without Hypocriſie.</hi> And ſo the God of Peace eſtabliſh your Hearts in his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Truth and Righteouſneſs for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi> I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned Friend, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>The</hi> 3<hi>d of the 11th Month,</hi> 1669.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>This to be read amongſt Friends.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Loving Advertiſement unto all thoſe who joyn together to Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Innocent.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PIlate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> conſulted together in this abominable Work, and were made Friends; although before they were at en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as you may ſee in <hi>Luke</hi> 23. And in the ſame Chapter you may read how <hi>Pilate</hi> called together the High Prieſts, the Rulers, and the People, who had joyned together, and falſly and vehemently accuſed the Innocent; and when thoſe Perſecutors were come (mark how <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Words run;) <hi>Ye have brought this</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54975:16"/> 
               <hi>man unto me, as one that perverteth the people: Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have examined him before you, and I find no fault in him:</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their many Accuſations, as you may read of in that Chapter; no, nor yet <hi>Herod</hi> neither; for <hi>Pilate</hi> ſent him to <hi>Herod</hi> to be examined, and they found no cauſe for what they did, as <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf confeſſeth no leſs than three times before them all, as you may ſee in <hi>ver.</hi> 22. and yet for all this, thoſe wicked Perſecutors Enmity was ſo great againſt the Truth, and their Love to Chriſt Jeſus ſo ſmall, that they joyned together with <hi>Judas</hi> their Informer, and crucified the Holy One. Oh conſider this, you wicked Perſecutors, who have ſet your Hands to the Devil's Work! did he not enter into <hi>Judas</hi> before he inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Chriſt? O conſider whoſe Work you are a doing! and ſee whether the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures do not teſtifie againſt the ſame ever ſince <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel?</hi> Oh be adviſed, and do not ſlay God's Witneſs in your Hearts, as <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> and the reſt of that wicked Crew did! for you may ſee there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> which let them ſee there was no fault in Jeſus; they had a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him in their Hearts, which if they had loved and obeyed, they would not have ſlain the Lord of Life: But they did then, as you do now, rebelled againſt it, and counted it of no value, and choſe rather to pleaſe wicked Men, who did then, as you are now
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54975:17"/> doing; they brought their Law to cover their Wickedneſs; and ſaid, <hi>By their Law he ought to die;</hi> and ſo they violated the righteous Law of God, which is Light, which manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in their Hearts there was no fault in him. Oh! conſider this, you envious Perſecutors, and turn to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which ſhineth in your dark Hearts, and read your States there; and ceaſe your evil doing before it be too late, leſt the God of this World blind your Eyes, and harden your Hearts, and bring you to deſtruction, as he did <hi>Judas,</hi> who was a Reſiſter of the Light; I ſhall appeal to the Witneſs for God in your Hearts, and come let us be tryed by it: Have you not done as bad as thoſe before mentioned, yea rather worſe? for you have reproachfully ſlandered, and falſly accuſed us behind our back, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many of us to ſuffer the loſs of our Goods, without Examination or Accuſation to our Faces; in this you out-ſtript the Cruelty of thoſe before-named, and the Heathen alſo; for they permitted <hi>Paul</hi> to be examined, and alſo to ſpeak for himſelf, as you may ſee in the Scripture, which you call your Rule, and yet do err, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God; for if you did, you would not wrong and perſecute your innocent Neighbours, who do you no harm, but deſire the everlaſting Good of all, even of our greateſt Enemies. Oh, do you do by us as you would have us do by you. Would you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54975:17"/> have us perſecute and tear away your Goods, becauſe you go to your Worſhip? or becauſe you will not come to ours? or would you not think it very hard to be ſo dealt by? Oh, come and be tryed by your own Rule! and read from the beginning to the end, and ſee whether the Perſecutors were not the falſe Worſhippers in all Generations, and the true Ones the Sufferers; and were not they as high in their Wiſdom and Learning as you are, who crucified Chriſt, and ſet your Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal over his Head, of <hi>Greek, Hebrew</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine?</hi> and they counted him of too low a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree for them to receive, and they mocked, and ſcoffed, and derided him, and thereby manifeſted their Enmity againſt him and his Followers then, as you do yours now againſt us.</p>
            <p>Come down, you High-minded Perſecutors, and bow before the Lord, and turn to his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in your Hearts which reprove you in ſecret, and teſtifie for us; and it hath made many of you to confeſs to our innocency and harmleſneſs, notwithſtanding the many falſe Aſperſions that the Wicked have caſt upon us; and although we have a Witneſs in your Hearts for us, yet your Mercies are ſtill Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties towards us. Oh, do not think to hide your ſelves from the All-ſeeing Eye of the Lord! for aſſuredly his righteous Judgments will find you out, and then all falſe Coverings will be too narrow: Do you think your Law
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54975:18"/> will plead for you then, or them who ſet it forth excuſe you? Oh no! then the righteous Law of God, which you have violated and broken, and diſobeyed now, will then riſe up in Judgment, and bear Witneſs againſt you; therefore leave off all your falſe Coverings for your Perſecution; for they are but deceit, and will deceive you, and ſtand you in no ſtead when you come to account for your deeds done in the body.</p>
            <p>And now you of my Neighbours and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who reſiſt the Spirit of the Lord, and follow the Imaginations of your own dark Hearts, and boaſt your ſelves in Wickedneſs: As your Fore-fathers did, ſo do you; they boaſted and ſaid, <hi>They had the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and were</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Seed, and had one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even God;</hi> and yet Chriſt told them plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>They were of their Father the Devil, and his works they were doing:</hi> and ſo are you now, who are a ſtriving againſt thoſe who worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth.</p>
            <p>Oh do not ſtrive to limit the Holy Spirit of the Lord, which is but one in the Male and in the Female! Were not the Scripture's Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to be fulfill'd? Oh! when will you witneſs that Saying fulfill'd, which ſaith on this wiſe, <hi>I will pour forth of my Spirit upon all Fleſh, and my Sons and my Daughters ſhall propheſie?</hi> [Mark] It's the Sons and Daughters of the Lord that are led by his Spirit, and not the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors. Whilſt I walk'd with you in the broad
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54975:18"/> way, which leadeth to Deſtruction, you did not perſecute me; but when it pleas'd the Lord to turn me from Darkneſs unto Light, and from Satan's power unto his own, then your Enmity began: But when I went along with you to your Worſhip, I had what this World could afford of the Fatneſs and Fulneſs thereof; but I muſt needs tell you, I had Lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in my Soul. Oh ſearch and try whether it be not ſo with you, who have gone this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years! For I went with as much Zeal as any of you; therefore let not your blind Zeal deceive you: I turn'd not from you through Enmity againſt you, but becauſe that dead Worſhip deceiv'd my Soul; for when Chriſt Jeſus, through his Love unto my Soul, did make known his Light in my Heart, which ſhew'd me the narrow Way, which leadeth unto Life; then I choſe rather to ſuffer with the People of God, than to enjoy your Favour, or all the Pleaſures, or Profits, or Honour this World can afford.</p>
            <p>And all you that think ye are a doing, as you ſhould do, turn unto the Light, that you may ſee what you are a doing; and may become from Perſecutors to be Sufferers, even as <hi>Paul</hi> was, through his obedience unto the Light, and he thought when he was in Darkneſs and blind Zeal, that he did as he ſhould do: Oh! therefore take you heed, and be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger deceiv'd, but turn unto the Light, before it be too late; for the Time haſteneth and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54975:19"/> away, and there is nothing elſe that will ſtand you in ſtead when Time ſhall be no more: O therefore be awakened and ariſe from the Dead, that Chriſt Jeſus may be your Light and your Leader, as he was <hi>David</hi>'s: For what doth it profit you to read the Scriptures, or to hear of the Promiſes or Mercies of the Lord unto the Children of Light? This will ſtand you in no ſtead, whilſt you your ſelves are in Darkneſs, and under the ſhadow of Death. Oh do not heap up that unto your ſelves, which you have no right unto! for you are in the Darkneſs, in the Perſecuting ſtate, which was, and is always blind: And how dare you in ſuch a ſtate to appear before the Lord? Do you think his all-ſeeing Eye doth not behold your Doings? Yes verily; and his Righteous Judgments aſſuredly will find you out; and then all your talking of that you live not in, will do you no good.</p>
            <p>How often have you and your Teachers been reading and talking of loving Enemies, and of walking in the Light, as Chriſt is in the Light, and many ſuch like things? and yet are found hating of your Souls Friends, who are telling you the Truth, and reproving you for Evil; and you are ſo far from walking in the Light, that you remain in your Sins, and plead for ſo doing until the laſt: Do you think that the Lord will be limited by you until the laſt Hour?</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:54975:19"/>
            <p> Oh turn to the Reproofs of his Light in your hearts, which maketh manifeſt the evil of your ways, whil'ſt the Day of God's Love laſteth unto you! that through his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments your Souls may come to be redeemed; for it's through Judgment that <hi>Sion</hi> witneſſeth Redemption, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart loveth Judgment; and if you will obey the Light, it will lead you into Judgment; and when you come to witneſs, your Souls re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd thereby, then you will witneſs <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s ſtate, who ſaid, <hi>O Lord, how I love thy judgments!</hi> and he deſir'd the Lord <hi>to ſend forth his Truth and his Light, to lead him;</hi> and it was his Law, and he walk'd in it: And if you would do ſo, you would have the Royal Law of Love in your hearts; and then you would have Fellowſhip with Jeſus, and feel the Effects of his Blood to cleanſe you from all ſin on this the Grave, and then you will plead no longer to ſtrengthen the Devil's Kingdom; for, if you die in your ſins, you will add greatly to his Kingdom; for thoſe that live and die in their ſins do never inherit the Kingdom of Heaven; for no unclean thing can come there, but they are for the Lake that burneth for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 9<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Day of the 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Month,</hi> 1670.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By one that wiſhes well to all Souls,</hi> Joan Vokins.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54975:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Friends at and nigh</hi> Colebrook <hi>and</hi> Longford <hi>Meeting, and thereaway.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Frinds,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Having you often in mind, thought it long before I could ſend a few Lines, having kept my Bed this three Months or more, and have not been able to write; and I am very weak ſtill, I could not go from my Bed: But hearing of an opportunity, have in much weakneſs written that which lay moſt upon my Mind, which is for the building of you up in the moſt Holy Faith, and encouraging of you in Well-doing.</p>
            <p>Oh my dear and tender Friends, feel the tender Love of the God of Love, that we may magnifie his Name together, though at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in Perſon: O the unutterable Loving-Kindneſs of our God, what Tongue can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it? how hath he preſerv'd us, &amp; provided for us hitherto, beyond what our hearts could deſire! Hath he not done that for us which none other could do? Hath he not delivered out of Dangers deep, and Difficulties many? Or hath he been ever wanting to us in doing us good? Oh ſurely no; but he hath multiplied his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and encreaſed Bleſſings frequently, and freely, as he in his Wiſdom ſees what is moſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54975:20"/> convenient for us: and if he pleaſe to feed us with the Bread of Affliction, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Adverſity; yet let us to his Teachings keep, that we may learn to profit thereby: Have not the trials and exerciſes of our Faith and Patience, brought us to a good Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Love of our God? O let us keep a narrow watch over our Hearts, that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy may not ſubtilly creep in under any pretence: for if he be harkened to, he will weaken the Faith, and Unbelief will enter, and then the murmuring Spirit will be ready to charge the Lord fooliſhly. Oh dear Hearts, our tender Father is not wanting, but is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help in all our needs: therefore let it be the whole and ſole bent of our minds to perform our Duties unto him.</p>
            <p>Oh up and be doing, for the time is come that none muſt be idle; but all that would have the wages of well-doing, muſt be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful every one in his place; and none to make excuſes: for Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt our Head is full of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and Strength, and Might, and ready to communicate to all his Members a ſuitable and ſeaſonable ſupply at all times: and if we (as diligent Servants) wait on him, our tender Maſter, he will diſcover our particular Duties, and ſhew us what is required of us. Oh let us go on with Courage unanimouſly, that we may be helpful one unto another, and ſo bring honour to our Head, that we may feel his Power ſupporting of us upon all occaſions, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54975:21"/> we may not doubt nor faint in our Minds by reaſon of the buffettings of the power of Darkneſs; but through the Faith in Chriſt Jeſus we may obtain Victory over all that would hinder the proſperity of Truth, and keep it under: for Truth muſt reign, and the Lord will be honoured in the dominion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And he will ſweep the Nation with the Beeſom of his Wrath; and the Hypocrites ſhall be tried, and fear ſhall ſurprize them, and woe will be to them that are at eaſe in <hi>Sion:</hi> but well will it be with them who think no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too dear to part with for the Truth ſake, whoſe Hearts are ſingly reſigned to ſerve the Lord with all that he hath given them, which is no more but our reaſonable Duties, which we have good cauſe diligently to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, unto the end, that we may daily feel the vertue of Life continued and renewed to us unto the end; and in the end a double reward, which our God hath prepared for all that hold out and endure thereunto: Bleſſed be his Holy Name for ever, and for evermore.</p>
            <p>Dear Friends, feel me in that which thinks no evil, and in it receive my Salutation, that it may reach unto the ſame in you: that we may breath one for another, and be refreſhed as Members of one Body: We cannot ſay one unto another, I have no need of thee; for there is work for us all in the Vineyard: Oh let us be diligent while we have time, that we may receive our Peny of Life to the comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54975:21"/> of our Souls every day; for we do not ſerve a hard Maſter.</p>
            <p>So in that which engages to his ſervice do I bid you farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>The 1ſt of the 6th Month,</hi> 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Friend in that which engages our Hearts to ſerve our God faithfully without any reſerve, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Some account given forth by</hi> Joan Vokins <hi>of the great Goodneſs and Mercy of the Lord towards her, and of the wonderful Works that he hath done for her; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to his Glory and her great Joy and Comfort: Written with her own Hand (a few Months before her deceaſe) as followeth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SOmthing of the tender dealing of the Lord with me ever ſince my Childhood, for (bleſſed be his Name) he preſerved me from many Evils that Youth is often enſnared with; and by his Light (that I then had no acquaintance with) ſhewed me the vanity and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54975:22"/> vain Cuſtoms of the World when I was very young, and all along my youth his Good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit did ſtill ſtrive with me to preſerve me from Sin and Evil: And if I had at any time, through perſuaſion of others, gone to that they called Recreation, I ſhould be ſo condemned for paſſing away my precious time, that I could have no peace, ſo that I could take no delight in their Paſtime, but was ſtill condemned. And many times I cried to the Righteous God to reveal his way unto me; and I promiſed to walk therein whatever I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured. For the ſnares of the World, the Lord was pleaſed to diſcover, and in ſome meaſure to make known the Croſs of Jeſus that Crucifies unto the World; and as I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to take it up and follow Jeſus through the many Tribulations, he endowed me with his Almighty Power, wherein hath been my help, bleſſed be his Worthy Name for ever: for his Loving-Kindneſs never fails, but his Mercies endure for ever: and his great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and tender Dealing towards my Soul, when in Darkneſs and under the Region of the Shadow of Death, is never to be forgotten; for it hath been largely extended unto me, when in deep diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>When my cry was often, Lord reveal thy Way unto me, that I may walk therein, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I undergo. But when I found the way ſo ſtrait and narrow, I could very willingly have turned aſide for eaſe; for Fleſh and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54975:22"/> Blood could not bear that which I had then to undergo; but bleſſed and renowned be the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, my Comforter, which leads into all Truth; for when I was in a dejected conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about <hi>Reprobation</hi> and <hi>Election,</hi> neither <hi>Prieſt</hi> nor <hi>Profeſſor</hi> could open the Myſtery of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation;</hi> but the Spirit of Light and Life (which is the Spirit of Jeſus) opened my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and revealed the Myſtery of the two Seeds, how that the one is for ever bleſſed, and the other curſed: And alſo what Happineſs might be received by taking heed to the Light that ſhined in my Heart, which makes manifeſt, that the way to the Crown of Glory is through the daily croſs to my own Will, and to take Chriſt's Yoke upon that Nature that would not be ſubject. Oh how precious is the Counſel of him who ſaid, <hi>Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for my yoke is eaſie, and my burden is light, and ye ſhall find reſt for your ſouls:</hi> And that Reſt I ſorely wanted, until I learned of Jeſus to be meek and low in Heart, and to ſuffer for well-doing; and then (glory unto his Holy Name for ever) his bleſſed Reward my Soul was daily made a partaker of; though hated by evil doers, yet loved by the Lord, and that engaged me to give up to his diſpoſe, and to anſwer his requirings, not account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf, nor any thing he hath give me, too much to part with, that the Truth may be propagated, and my tender God hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: For (bleſſed be his Worthy Name) he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54975:23"/> hath filled my Cup, with the ſweet Salvation of his Son Chriſt Jeſus, the Light and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of his poor and helpleſs Ones, who have no other to depend upon for Help at all times, but wait daily to be furniſhed upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion to ſerve him in all Faithfulneſs; for he is Worthy, my Soul can truly ſay, for he gave me of his good Spirit, and it was with me (yet unknown) when I rebelled againſt it, and was not willing to be ſubject to its Leadings, nor obſerving of its Dictates as I ought to have been: Oh then did I want power (as many do now) not knowing the ſufficiency of the engrafted Word of God's Grace that is able to ſave: But when I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed its counſel, I found it ſufficient to bring good to me, out of great afflictions, beyond my expectation; and then could I plead no excuſe, knowing that unto the Lord Jeſus (who had brought great things to paſs) I muſt give my account: for he hath manifeſted his Power, and I have cauſe to believe it will never fail towards his People, if we fail not to obey the manifeſtation of it; but Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs is required to the Talent received, for which we muſt give an account; and then what can ſtand us in ſtead, if we have not an increaſe? This was my concern for many Years, and I could not take comfort in Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or Children, Houſe, or Land, or any viſibles, for want of the Marriage Union with the Lamb of God, that takes away the ſins of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54975:23"/> the Souls of thoſe that cannot be ſatisfied in them; but are weary of the burden of them, as I was; and God by his Spirit ſhewed me, he abhorred my ſelf-righteouſneſs; and let me ſee that in him was Righteouſneſs, Life and Power; and then I was ſenſible that he is the the Light of the World, that enlightens eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that comes into the World; and that it was ſtriving with me from my Youth, which was before ever I heard the name <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker;</hi> and then I did believe that there was a People or Church over whom Chriſt Jeſus was Head, though I could yet not find them, nor be a Member of them; yet long ſought after it ſorrowfully, with many ſtrong and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent cries and deſires: But the Lord in his own due time anſwered my weary Soul, and made known more and more of the way of his Truth and People, and at length ſent ſome of his Meſſengers, as Inſtruments in his Hand, for my Encouragement and Confirmation: Then was I, and many deſolate Ones, right glad (whoſe Souls had long languiſhed) for the glad Tidings that they brought with them, how that we might inherit Subſtance which we had long ſought and been ſearching for, both in the Scriptures, and amongſt Profeſſors of many ſorts of Profeſſion; for we would fain have filled our Souls with the Husks, but that could not ſatisfie, we knew not the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Health of him who ſaid, <hi>I wiſdom lead in the midſt of the Paths of Judgment, to teach</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54975:24"/> 
               <hi>them that love and follow me to inherit Subſtance:</hi> Oh this is that which did at firſt convince us, and tendered our Hearts in the beginning: Then what was too near or dear for us to part with in the Day of our deep Diſtreſs, when none could cure our wounded Souls? Oh how precious was the Heart-ſearching Light when we firſt knew it to ſhine upon our Tabernacles, to guide us in the narrow Way wherein is Life, and perfect Peace for thoſe whoſe Minds are ſtaied on the Lord! And when I have read, that he would keep them in perfect Peace whoſe Minds are ſtaied on him, what would not I have done, that it might have been my condition? But then I could not watch nor wait, but was as a Ship without an Anchor among the mercileſs Waves; but Praiſes unto the Lord for ever, he cauſed the Living Hope to ſpring that anchored in try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Times. And I was, even as <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the <hi>red Sea,</hi> compaſſed all round on every Hand; great was the ſtrait that I was then in, much hardſhip; the Sea before, and the Enemy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting ſo much impoſſibility, that his proud Waves of Temptations, Buffettings, and falſe Accuſations had almoſt ſunk me under: Oh then did I cry unto the God of Mercy and tender Compaſſion, that I might but ſtand ſtill and behold his Salvation; and he did ariſe and rebuke the Enemy, and made way for me to travel on in my Heavenly Progreſs, and overturned the Mountains that were on each
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54975:24"/> hand, and diſmaied <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt (which I may compare my Relations and the Profeſſors unto,) for they purſued me and made my Suffering great, till they had wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried themſelves; and their Oppreſſion was ſo ſore, that I ſomtimes was ready to faint, and even to ſay, Surely, I ſhall one Day fall; but Living Praiſes unto the Almighty, he hath made me a partaker of the ſure Mercies of <hi>David,</hi> and hath ſubdued Truth's Enemies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and kept and preſerved me faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, till ſeveral of my Relations were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that God's Power was with me; and now when my Husband, and Chhildren, and Relations are with me in a good Meeting, and the Powerful Preſence of the Lord is amongſt us; it is a bleſſed Reward for all, for one Soul is more worth than all the World, as ſaith the Scripture: Therefore Faithfulneſs is very needful, for it doth produce a good effect, whatever we may endure; for the momentary Affliction that we meet with here, doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a further weight of Glory hereafter; and in the ſenſe of the ſame my Head was born up to endure hardſhips, when I could willingly have hid or gotten eaſe; but I conſidered that I could not hide from the Lord, who brought to my remembrance my Promiſe that I made before his Way was revealed to me; and if I broke Covenant with the Lord, I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into his Reſt: Oh then a ſuffering in the Fleſh, and a ceaſing from Sin, was the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54975:25"/> delight of my Soul; although the Enemy ceaſed not, but Night and Day, as a roaring Lyon, and a cunning Hunter, ſeeking for the precious Life, and chaſed my poor Soul as a Partridge on the Mountains; but my God had ſhewed me that the way to Reſt was through many Troubles, and that he would be at hand to Deliver out of them all by his Almighty Power: (but I could hardly truſt it then,) but yet, turning to it, I found Preſervation by it, when the backſliding of ſome had like to have cauſed me to ſtumble; but the unerring Spirit of Jeſus ſhewed me that if thouſands fall on the one hand, and tens of thouſands on the other, that ſhould not defile me; and if all the reſt were Righteous, that ſhould not juſtifie me, if I did not obey the Truth, now he had made known his Covenant of Life, which I ſo deeply engaged to be faithful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and then I turned my back on the World, and all the friendſhip and glory of it, that I might obtain the favour of Jeſus, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned me for my Self-righteouſneſs, as for my known Sins, for I was cautious of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt the Lord ever ſince my Youth, and deſired after the beſt Religion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and when I was very young in years, I greatly delighted to go to Profeſſors Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and could bring home the Text, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat much of their Sermons, but yet that brought no benefit to my poor hungry Soul: And when I was in ſecret, before the all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54975:25"/> Eye of the Lord, he adminiſtred Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon it all, and I had no Peace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; although none could condemn me for any miſdemeanor, as outwardly; but when my own Righteouſneſs became loathſome to me, then was I made willing to part with all that had been near and dear unto me, that I might feel and witneſs the Robe of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs revealed, and be cloathed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And as for my Husband and Children, my true and tender Love was ſo great, that I could have done or ſuffered much for them: But if I had diſobeyed the Lord, to pleaſe them, I might have provoked him to have withholden his Mercies from us all, and to bring his Judgments upon us; And then who ſhall excuſe in the Day of Accompt? Then if a Man (as the Scripture ſays) ſhould give the Fruit of his Body for the Sin of his Soul, it will not be accepted. Then Husbands, and Wives, and Parents, and Children, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſhall all receive according to their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and none that diſobeys the Lord can be excuſed, no more than <hi>Adam</hi> was, when he ſaid, That the Woman gave him the forbidden Fruit, and he did eat, and ſo provoked the Lord, that the Curſe came upon himſelf, and could not be excuſed. And although Man and Wife ſhould be helpful one to another in Righteouſneſs, yet too many there are, ſince the fall, that hinder and hurt each other, for which an account muſt be given anavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54975:26"/> And this did I conſider many a time, and earneſtly endeavour to avoid; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the falſe Aſperſions that might ariſe, yet I ſtill endeavoured to keep my Conſcience clear in the ſight of my tender God; and none can lay any thing to my Charge, except it be for ſerving the Living and True God, though in that way that many may call <hi>Hereſie,</hi> yet I do worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth. For as Chriſt Jeſus hath ſaid, it is come to paſs, that our Heavenly Father ſeeketh ſuch, and always ſought ſuch to worſhip him, in his own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual way of Worſhip; which ſhall ſtand, when all Idolatry and invented Worſhips ſhall fall.</p>
            <p>Written aboard the firſt Ship <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The 1ſt month,</hi> 1680.</note> as I went to <hi>New-England,</hi> when none that ſaw me, expected my life; but the Lord was with me, and relieved me, and his bleſſed Power raiſed me, as at many other times.</p>
            <p>And I arrived at <hi>New York</hi> the 4th Day of the 3d Month, 80, and a Maiden Friend, whoſe Name was <hi>Sarah Yoklet,</hi> went with me from <hi>England,</hi> and travelled with me until I came to <hi>Oyſter-Bay</hi> in <hi>Long-Iſland;</hi> and the Lord ſo ordered it, that when ſhe left me, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Woman-Friend, that had a Teſtimony, was my Companion ſeveral Months, whoſe name was <hi>Lydia Wright.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh matchleſs Mercies of the Lord, who can rightly conſider them as they have been
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54975:26"/> manifeſted, and not be tendered, as I am! Oh how long did his tender Spirit ſtrive with me before I gave up to go to Sea? How did his long Patience wait and ſuffer? Surely it's worthy to be remembred; for he might have cut me off in a diſobedient Condition: But bleſſed and magnified be his Heart-tendering Power; it bowed me from Year to Year, and brought me into Subjection, when in a low Condition I could not help my ſelf, nor had no other to help me: Oh then did it ſupport me in Exerciſes, ſore both in Body and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; when my Mind hath been ſo dejected, that my Faith almoſt failed, then did my tender Father, through the Son of his Love, Chriſt Jeſus, yeild me ſweet relief, though in a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Land, and ſweetly encouraged me to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel on; and many ſweet Promiſes, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gave me, as I ſtood ſingly reſigned to obey his Commands, and be at his diſpoſe, he was never wanting to fulfil; but by Sea and Land hath multiplied his Mercies, <hi>and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a right Spirit in me,</hi> to the reſolving of Doubts, and caſting out of falſe Fears (ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Praiſes to his moſt holy Name); for often did that cauſe Torment, when the dark Reaſoner was very buſie: Then did I cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and ſay, Surely thou knoweſt all, and I have none but thee to help, and many Eyes are over me, and great Difficulties ſurround me on every hand, and I am the pooreſt and weakeſt that I do know; and if
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54975:27"/> I ſhould fail by the way, how would the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my rejoice, and the Truth be reproached? And much buffeting did I undergo in my long and ſore Exerciſes; but as I caſt my Care up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, he hath cared for me; and bleſſed be his Name, he hath helped in my greateſt ſtraits, and hath made hard things eaſie, and what he ſhewed me by his pure Spirit of Light for my encouragement, before I came forth, he hath brought to paſs: Glory to his Name for ever, may all thoſe ſay with my Soul that love the Leadings of the Light of Jeſus; for though it leads through Tribulation, yet it brings the Soul ſweet Conſolation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worthy to be followed through the Self-denial; for it's through the daily Croſs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Reward of the Crown; and precious is the feeling of the Life of Jeſus to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened and illuminated Soul, and that made the roaring Sea, and dry Land, and loneſome Wilderneſs all one to me by Night and by Day; and great was my encouragement to commit all that my Heavenly Father had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, to his keeping, and to follow him, and in taking up the daily Croſs, I found Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to preſerve me from looking out at my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of Body, when ſorely exerciſed in Mind, ready to ſink under the oppreſſion of it; had not the Spirit of Truth, the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, helped my Infirmities, and taught me, I had never known how to pray as I ought; but I often read, That the Prayers of the Lord's
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54975:27"/> Children avail much with him, and in theſe latter Days, according to his Promiſe, his are taught by him, and in Righteouſneſs they ſhall be eſtabliſhed, and great ſhall be their Peace: and this is the Effect of our Heavenly Father's great unſpeakable Love to thoſe that watch unto Prayer, and continue in the ſame; for I know not how any can expect a Child's Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that breaks his Father's Commands, and does not repent; and who is it but knows that watching and waiting is generally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded? Surely it is a Duty that ought to be performed by every one that is come to an Underſtanding; and by believing in Jeſus, the Light and Power of God, all may receive ſtrength to perform it; and for want of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding how nigh he was to me in Years that are paſt, I was long in a deſolate Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and could not be ſatisfied without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the Teachings of his Spirit, which is light: But I was then in darkneſs, and under the ſhadow of Death, longing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the countenance of the Lord to ſhine upon my Tabernacle; for if it ſhould be diſſolved, I was not ſenſible of a better Building eternal in the Heavens; though I read of them that had, yet I knew not their Foundation; and whatſoever I builded, it came to loſs, till I knew Chriſt Jeſus, the Rock and ſure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Heavenly Building: And bleſſed be his Name, the Inſpiration of his Spirit is very precious, without which none can have a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54975:28"/> right Underſtanding; and I could not find peace with God while I did err for want of this good Underſtanding. And my Cry was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Lord, to give me an underſtanding Heart, that I might diſcern between things that differ; for the crooked Serpent, who is very ſubtle in his Workings, endeavours by Flattery and Threatnings, Temptations, Buffetings, and falſe Accuſations, to darken the Heart, and enfeeble the Mind; and if he cannot prevail ſo, he can transform himſelf into the likeneſs of an Angel of Light, to hinder the travelling ones, whoſe Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings begin to be opened, yet watching in the Light, they come to ſee his Snares; then he beſtirs him, as a ſtrong Man armed indeed, as by Experience much might be ſpoken, ſince I was firſt exerciſed about going this Voyage; but I ſhall omit as much as I can, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in my View but Truth's Proſperity, and preferring it above all, becauſe it's bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to me than all; I can do no leſs than bare my Teſtimony unto all People, That it's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency far exceeds the choiceſt Gold, and the precious Pearls; and the Spirit of Truth comforts the comfortleſs, and ſtrengthens the weak, and relieves the needy: Oh what can be compared to its Power! for it works a change of the Heart, and preſerves from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt the Lord, all thoſe that follow the Leadings of the Light thereof unto amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Life, and honours the Lord by order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54975:28"/> their Converſation aright, according to the Dictates of his Spirit. Oh, I had rather mourn away all my Days than grieve it, or walk contrary to it, whatever Reproach I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; for I have had a bleſſed Reward when I have obſerved it, and obeyed it; and I hope I ſhall never forget how the Power of it brought me into Subjection, and made me wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be diſpoſed of by it; and when it had wrought me into a ſingle Reſignment, then was my weighty Concern (touching my Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>New England)</hi> taken off, and a Service laid upon me to go back, and labour for the Settlement of our Womens Meetings in our County of <hi>Berks,</hi> which was no ſmall Croſs to take up: But as I daily followed Jeſus, (ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured be his worthy Name) he endowed me with his eternal encouraging Power, and alſo ſtrengthned the weak and hindermoſt of the Flock; though <hi>Amalek</hi> lay in wait by the way, and the oppoſite Spirit did ſtrongly ſtrive; yet our good Shepherd did viſit his Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids, and (bleſſed be his Name) filled us with his overcoming Power, when the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in <hi>Iſrael</hi> were ſo diſmayed, as we were likely to have loſt our Womens Meeting; but Praiſes, Honour, and Renown, be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto that Almighty Power that hath ſet up and ſetled this Womens Meeting, ſaith my Soul; for it hath been a good Reward to me, and fitly furniſhed me for the Service that was required, and wonderfully upheld me therein
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54975:29"/> unto admiration; and I can truly ſay, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is ſufficient, and can give in a true Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, that the Lord owns our Womens Meetings, and hath manifeſted and magnified his excellent Power therein, to the gladding of our Hearts, and the refreſhing of our Souls wherever I came. Glory to his Name, and magnified be his preſerving Power for ever: He is a God of Wiſdom unto the Fooliſh, and Strength unto the Weak, and honours his Power in contemptible Veſſels, that it may have its due; for all Honour belongs thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: But thoſe that are in the Wiſdom of the World, which comes from beneath, and have many Arts and Parts, and mind not the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that comes from above, they take that to themſelves which belongs to God, and that provokes him to Wrath; and he is angry with ſuch as ſeek Honour one of another, and do not ſeek his Honour more than their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and Honour to Man; for that hath been the overthrow of many; for God is jealous of his Glory, <hi>he will not give it to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, nor his praiſe to graven Images;</hi> but the ſecret Arm of his Power is ſtretched out to overturn them, and he is on his way, and it's in vain for <hi>Fleſh to ſtrive againſt him, before whom all Nations are but as the drop of a Bucket: for out of the Mouths of Babes and Sucklings he will perfect his praiſe,</hi> both in Males and Females that give up to ſerve him; and he brings great things to paſs, contrary to Man's Wiſdom or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54975:29"/> Expectation, that <hi>no Fleſh might glory in his Preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For when I was exerciſed about ſetling the Womens Meeting, I little thought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned again with going for <hi>New England;</hi> but after a ſhort time it was more weighty than ever, and my Exerciſes more than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and this I do write, that no one ſhould murmur, and ſay, <hi>No Exerciſe is like mine;</hi> and this followed me until the Hand of the All-wiſe God was ſo heavy upon me, that I could no longer ſtay at home, although both ſick and lame, and much to undergo both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and outwardly, yet did not dare to plead with the Lord any longer, or to make any Excuſe, but truly gave up all, both Life and all that he had given me, when he required it; and he brought me to be <hi>as Clay in the hand of the Potter.</hi> He filled my Veſſel with his Heavenly Treaſure, and fulfilled that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that teſtifies that he hath ſaid, <hi>I honour them that honour me;</hi> and bleſſed be the Lord, ſuch Honour have the Earthen Veſſels of a Remnant, and the Excellency of the Power is his, and the Glory of all; for he is worthy of it; for he is no hard Maſter, but a ſure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of his faithful Servants, and he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues them with Power that delights in his Law, and inclines to keep his Commands, and unto ſuch they are not grievous, but joyous; but looking out hinders; and therefore let none look at their own Weakneſs; let my
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54975:30"/> Harms make others beware, and let's be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on our good Phyſician; for he hath the Balm of <hi>Gilead</hi> that cures both Soul and Body, which makes the weak ſtrong, with the ſweet Cordials of his Life, that relieves the faint hearted and feeble minded, and through tender Mercy I have found it very needful, and very uſeful at all times in all Conditions; elſe what could I have done when in ſuch a weak Condition, ſo many Thouſands of Miles from my Habitation? but bleſſed be the Lord, and magnified be his preſerving Power; as Tryals did abound, Patience did ſuperabound, and that brought me to a good Experience of that which ſweetned my bitter Cups, and that cauſed the living Hope to ſpring, that anchors in ſtormy times; and then did the Light of my Soul's Beloved ſhine upon me, and he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me what great deliverances he had wrought for me, and what great cauſe I had to truſt in his Name, that had been a comfortable Refuge unto me at home and abroad, and alſo ſhewed me, that his <hi>Rod and Staff had comforted me;</hi> and he was always with me, and in the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Preſence did my Soul rejoice in the midſt of great Tryals, and then was my cry, <hi>Lord, give me and mine the comfortable enjoyment of thy preſence for ever, and then try us as thou pleaſeſt: Thy preſerving Power is all that I deſire of thee, and unto it I commit all, and with thee I leave all; for thou art worthy to diſpoſe of all; and then would Life flow in as a River, to the comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54975:30"/> 
               <hi>and ſtrengthening of Soul and Body. Everl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Praiſes, and holy Thanksgivings be returned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Chriſt Jeſus; for he is worthy, my Soul can truly ſay; for I have experienced his dealings, and ſeen his mighty works that he hath done, even marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly for his tender Seed, with which my Soul hath travelled, and is often concerned; for they have much to bear wherever I have been. The Lord my God relieve them more and more, and work their deliverance for thy own Glory, and the comfort of thy true travelling ones for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written aboard the Ship in</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>ths</hi> 3<hi>d Month,</hi> Anno 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>A further Testimony for the magnifying of that Power that ſupported my weak Body, and comforted my poor Soul in my Travels in</hi> America: <hi>I feel my ſelf concerned to give a Relation of ſome particular Places and Service.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt I came to <hi>New York,</hi> and there had been hurt done by ſome, that Friends had loſt their <hi>5th</hi> Day Meeting, and I laboured to ſettle it again, and God's Eternal Power wrought wonderfully in me in ſeveral Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with his people, and we were well refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And when the Meeting aforeſaid was ſetled again, it was with me to go to <hi>Long Iſland,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54975:31"/> there the <hi>Ranters</hi> oppreſſed <hi>Friends,</hi> but the Lord had a tender People there, and his Power was amongſt them, and we were ſweetly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed together; for God's <hi>Almighty Power was over all,</hi> in all our Meetings wherever I came, to the ſubduing of the dark Power that raged in the <hi>Ranters,</hi> and the relieving of the tender hearted: Honour and Praiſes be aſcribed unto it for ever; for it made me ſenſible of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the tender Seed, and for its ſake my Soul was in a deep travel; and the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the general Meeting, I was near unto death, and many <hi>Friends</hi> were with me, who did not expect my Life, and I was ſo weak when I came there, that two <hi>Women-Friends</hi> led me into the Meeting, and there was a great Meeting of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts of people, and in a little time the God of Wiſdom, Life and Power, filled me with the Word of his Power, and I ſtood up in the ſtrength thereof, and it was ſo prevailing over the Meeting, that <hi>Friends</hi> were very much comforted and refreſhed, and the Power of Darkneſs ſo chained, that the oppoſing <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Apoſtates</hi> could not ſhew their antick tricks, nor oppreſs <hi>Friends,</hi> as they did uſe to do; for they were very abuſive in thoſe remote Iſlands, and commonly did much Miſchief in <hi>Friends</hi> Meetings: And they that had been convinced, and were <hi>turned again with the Dog to his Vomit,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture, and with the <hi>Sow that was waſhed, to wallow again in the mire, and had made Shipwreck of Faith and a good Conſcience,</hi> they were moſt wicked; and preached Scripture,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54975:31"/> and had Truth's Words, and grieved Truth's Spirit, and burdened <hi>Friends</hi> exceedingly, and honeſt <hi>Friends</hi> could hardly be clear, that had a Teſtimony, except they ſpake while they were ſpeaking: But when God's Power did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe over them, it many times put them to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, even to admiration; and altho <hi>Friends</hi> Exerciſe was great, eſpecially them that decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet the bleſſed Effect of the Almighty Power was, and is a precious Recompence, and a good Reward.</p>
            <p>And when my Service was over in <hi>Long I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland,</hi> it was in my Heart to go to <hi>Road Iſland,</hi> to the General Meeting that approached ſoon after I arrived there; yet we had a quick paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, through Providence; and when I came to the General Meeting of <hi>Friends,</hi> there was that abominable Crew, and <hi>Tho. Caſe,</hi> the grand <hi>Ranter,</hi> was bawling very loud; and I had been there but a very little time, but God's living Power did ariſe moſt wonderfully, and I decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the demonſtration thereof, and ſoon put him to ſilence; and he went forth, and the powerful Preſence of the Lord was amongſt his People; and this General Meeting in <hi>Road Iſland</hi> laſted Four Days together, and I had good Service there, and God's Eternal Heart-tendering Power was over all, Glory and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Praiſes be unto it for evermore.</p>
            <p>And ſtill it was upon me to go to <hi>Boſton;</hi> for that was with me before I came from home; and I haſtened to take a paſſage in a Sloop, and went with ſome <hi>Friends,</hi> and one was a <hi>Maiden</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:54975:32"/> 
               <hi>Friend,</hi> that had a few Words ſometimes in Meetings, who had been there once before, and ſhe and another <hi>Friend</hi> ſuffered much there, both Impriſonment and other Cruelty, for Conſcience-ſake: But bleſſed be the God of all our Mercies, we had peaceable Meetings there, and his excellent Power was ſo, that it tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the people, and there was hardly any that I ſaw, but ſhed tears; there was a <hi>Lawyer</hi> that had a hand in the ſuffering of our <hi>Friends</hi> that were put to Death, and he was very ſolid all the while. And after this I travelled by Sea and Land in the ſtrength of the ſupporting Power to many places, whitherſoever the Lord order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me; and as I followed the Line of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light, he failed not to endow me with the renewing of his precious Power, and my Soul hath cauſe to magniſie it, becauſe it enabled me to anſwer what the Lord required of me, and fitted me, who was the moſt unfit, and the pooreſt and moſt helpleſs that ever I did ſee concerned in ſuch a Service: But it was the more to the Honour of the Power of my God that ſo wonderfully wrought in my poor weak and helpleſs Veſſel; and many <hi>Friends</hi> were tendered thereby (in many places in the ſenſe of my Weakneſs). Honoured and Renowned be it for ever, ſaith my Soul; for its Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made the Hearts of his People glad, and we were well refreſhed together in all the Meetings that I was at in <hi>New England.</hi> And from thence I returned back to <hi>Road Iſland</hi> and <hi>Long Iſland;</hi> and when I was clear thereabout, I
<pb facs="tcp:54975:32"/> took Shipping for <hi>Eaſt Jerſey,</hi> and the Power of God was greatly manifeſted, and through his ſpecial Providence we were preſerved, being in great peril and danger of being caſt away when we were in ſight of Land; for the Winds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing boiſterous, and the foaming Sea in ſo great a Rage, that we could not caſt Anchor to ſtay the Veſſel, being near the Shoals; but the Lord who hath all Power in his hands, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us (Praiſes to his holy Name), and we ſafely landed at <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> (and <hi>Elizabeth Dean,</hi> that then travelled with me, was very ſick); and we had very good Meetings in <hi>Eaſt Jerſey,</hi> where I met with the Lord among his people, as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times, bleſſed be his Name; and after ſome time ſpent amongſt them, and that we had been well refreſhed with God's holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious living Power, it carried me from thence to <hi>Weſt Jerſey,</hi> and into ſome part of <hi>Penſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> (but it had not that Name then) and in the ſenſe of God's great Love to his tender Seed, I encouraged his Children to ſuffer, and to be careful that they did not cauſe Truth to ſuffer; for if they tendered it in their own Boſoms, and travell'd with it, the Lord would bring it over all its Enemies, and it ſhall reign over all in his due time; and bleſſed be his moſt worthy Name, he ſoon after brought it to paſs by his delivering Power; and when I had laboured that the Goſpel-Life might be lived in, and the Goſpel-Order eſtabliſhed amongſt them, there remained the heavenly power among the tender ones. And the Lord heard the cry of the poor,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54975:33"/> and granted the deſire of the needy, and viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with the Goſpel-Power; for a little time after I came home, I had an account, that they had Mens Meetings and Womens Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Goſpel-Light, Life and Power, and were eſtabliſhing in the Bleſſed Order that was teſtified of, when I was there with them.</p>
            <p>And when I was clear of <hi>West Jerſey,</hi> and thoſe parts, I returned to <hi>New York,</hi> in order to take my paſſage for <hi>England;</hi> but before I came there, the Living God (whom I ſerved with all my Heart) further tryed me, and laid it weightily upon me to go to <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> which was no little croſs to my Mind; but the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Power of the true and living God wrought ſo ſtrongly with me, that I was made willing to take up the <hi>Croſs, and follow Jeſus,</hi> through many Tribulations, and he (magnified be his Power) moſt wonderfully ſupported and conducted me all along: For I took Shipping at <hi>New York,</hi> and as the Lord put it into my Heart to viſit <hi>Friends</hi> in the <hi>Leeward Iſlands,</hi> ſo he carried the Veſſel, let them that ſail'd do what they could; and they could not ſteer their Courſe <hi>Barbadoes-Road,</hi> altho they endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with all their might; and I had good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice amongſt them in the Veſſel; and they were made to confeſs to the Almighty Power that I teſtified of; and we laid by <hi>Antego</hi> a Week be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Owner would let me go a-ſhore: But the All-wiſe God ordered it ſo, that the Veſſel could not go away till I had been there, and performed what Service he had appointed for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54975:33"/> me; and bleſſed be his Name, his Reward was precious; for we came a-ſhore on a Firſt Day, and I haſtened to a <hi>Friends</hi> Meeting; and when I came in, I found the Lord's Power was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his People, and I had a precious time with them: There was a little handful of plain hearted <hi>Friends,</hi> and our Hearts were tendered, and our Souls comforted, and we rejoiced that the Lord Jeſus had viſited us, and cauſed us in his Love to viſit each other.</p>
            <p>So when I returned to the Sea again, it came into my Heart to viſit <hi>Friends</hi> at <hi>Nevice;</hi> and when I had taken leave of <hi>Friends</hi> of <hi>Antego</hi> that came aboard with me, and God's Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power was with us, and ſweetly refreſhed our Souls, as we were aboard the Veſſel, and remained with us; and we were concerned one for another, not knowing that we ſhould ever ſee each others Faces more: But ſee how the Lord ordered it; as we were ſailing on the Sea, it opened in my Heart to viſit <hi>Friends</hi> at <hi>Nevice;</hi> but the Owner of the Veſſel being a hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical Profeſſer, cauſed my Exerciſe to be the more; but the Power of the Lord was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and <hi>the Winds and Sea obeyed,</hi> that we were carried to <hi>Nevice</hi> againſt his will; but he would not let me go a-ſhore; for he had heard, <hi>That thoſe ſhould pay a great Fine that carried any Friend thither;</hi> and hoyſted Sail again for <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and ſaid, he would weather the Point of <hi>Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopa;</hi> and he laboured Three Weeks, but could not do it: for the Hand of the Lord was againſt him; elſe he might have done it in a few Days,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54975:34"/> but he provoked the Lord, and truſted in his Veſſel, and in his own Skill; and he locked up the Bread, and dealt hardly with his Paſſengers when he ſaw he ſhould be longer at Sea than at firſt he did expect; and he knew that for Three Weeks there was ſtinking Water, and we were cloſe by a <hi>French</hi> Iſland, and they ſaid, the <hi>French</hi> would not let us h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve any, if we ſtarved: They were <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>If we came for water, they would take our Ship for a Prey, and us for Captives:</hi> And yet this Owner of the Veſſel would not go to any other Iſland, until the <hi>Merchants</hi> that were aboard threatned him very ſorely; and then he put in at a mountainous place, called <hi>Mount ſerat;</hi> and they went all away from me as ſoon as they were landed; for I was very weakly, being aboard the Veſſel ſo long, with ſuch bad Accommodation: I went aboard with my Clothes ſo wet, that I could wring Water out of them, and ſo dried them upon my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Body, which caſt me into ſuch a Feveriſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that I was very dry, and I ſate down on the Shoar, and a Girl came to fetch freſh Water near where I ſate, and I drank till I ſweat, and then I ſwooned, and lay ſome time; but the ariſing of the Life of Jeſus ſet me on my Feet again, and in the ſtrength and relief thereof I went to enquire for a paſſage for <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and heard of none; but I was not clear of <hi>Nevice,</hi> but hearing of a leaking Veſſel to go to <hi>Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> took my paſſage in that, hoping that way might be made from thence to go to <hi>Nevice,</hi> and then having got a paſſage, it being
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54975:34"/> Night and rainy, I tried to get me a Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Land, and the People were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, but the Lord did ſo order it, that I met with an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Woman, and ſhe treated me kindly, but ſhe had neither Bread nor Drink, but Wine and Sugar; and I deſired half a Pint of <hi>Madary</hi> Wine to be boiled, and that ſerved me Night and Morning, and the Lord bleſſed it to me, and his Holy Power ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied me; and, while I ſtaid for the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, I had good ſervice there, though there was no Friend in all the Iſland; they had baniſhed a Friend out of it, as I heard, but a little before, and the People told me they did not dare to have a Meeting, yet I publiſhed Truth in the Streets, and they confeſſed to it; and ſo I left Truth honorably amongſt them, and then came aboard the Veſſel, where I laſt took my Paſſage, and ſailed to the other Veſſel, that I had ſuffered in, and called for the Owner and cleared my Conſcience to him, and told him the Hand of the Lord was againſt him, and warned him to Repent, elſe he ſhould ſuddenly feel the ſtroak of it to be heavy upon him; and inaſmuch as his Heart had been too much ſet on that Bark, he ſhould ſhortly ſee that the Lord would deſtroy it, and accordingly his Veſſel was ſplit on a Rock in a little time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. So when I, through tender Mercy, came to <hi>Antego</hi> again, the Friends told me how they had been concerned for me, and ſo had <hi>Nevice</hi> Friends, and there was a Paſſage ready for <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> and an honeſt Woman-Friend, whoſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54975:35"/> name was <hi>Mary Humphery,</hi> was very ready to go with me, and Friends there were very joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of my coming, and we had many good and powerful Meetings in that Iſland; and there was a Judge and his Wife came to Meeting, and People of ſeveral ſorts, and we had ſome Meetings at the Houſes of them that were no Friends, and Friends were well ſatisfied and comforted, and the mighty Power of God was with us: Glory unto it, for it is worthy over all, and in us all: Oh that we may have an Eye to its Glory in our whole Lives and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations; for it is by it we live, move, and have our Being; and its dealing with us, and working for us in that place is worthy to be remembred; for this was the place that the Owner of the Veſſel aforementioned was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to carry me to; but the Lord was on my ſide, and prevented much Evil when it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; and the Governor of that Place was ſo kind that he gave us his Letter of Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to carry with us; and ſo I came back with <hi>M. Humphery</hi> to <hi>Antego</hi> and to <hi>Five Iſlands,</hi> and there we and ſome Friends that went with us viſited a poor People that complained of their Prieſt, and ſaid he came to them but once a Year, and then it was to take that which they had from them; and we had a precious opportunity to manifeſt the Truth, and they were very kind to us, and ſeem'd to be well ſatisfied and affected.</p>
            <p>And then I being clear, and a paſſage preſented for <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> as ſoon as I was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54975:35"/> ready I went aboard, and was there ſooner than could have been expected: And when I arrived, I met with many Friends at <hi>Bridg-Town,</hi> and there took an account of the Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meetings, and went to them and other Meetings as brief as I could; and moſt Days I had two or three Meetings of a Day, both among the Blacks, and alſo among the White People: And the Power of the Lord Jeſus was mightily manifeſted, ſo that my Soul was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten melted therewith, even in the Meetings of the <hi>Negro's</hi> or <hi>Blacks,</hi> as well as among Friends. And when I had gone through the Iſland, and was clear, having been well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with Friends, in the feeling of the Heavenly Power; and in the ſtrength of the ſame I came aboard the Ship for my Native Land again.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written a board the Ship coming from</hi> Barbadoes, <hi>in</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 3<hi>d Month,</hi> 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>BEfore I went to Sea I was two Weeks in the ſervice of Truth in <hi>Kent,</hi> and then it was ſhewed me, being at <hi>Sandwich,</hi> that I ſhould bear my Teſtimony for God, and his Divine Spiritual Worſhip, in a <hi>Steeple-Houſe</hi> there; and coming home, the Heavenly Power wrought mightily in my Heart. And when I was clear of thoſe Countreys, I was better in Health than I had been for many Years. And, as the Light of Jeſus ſhewed me before, I left <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:54975:36"/> as is afore hinted; ſo the Power thereof or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered me when I came back, &amp; it was ſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily on me before I came aſhore, that I thought it long ere I came to <hi>Kent</hi> to clear my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the God of Sea and Land brought me ſafely thither, and I haſtened to <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and on a <hi>Firſt-day,</hi> being the 5th of the 4th Month, 1681, I went to the <hi>Steeple-Houſe,</hi> as it was before me, and had been of a long time, and in the ſtrength of the Almighty Power I delivered that Meſſage which I received of the Lord Jeſus, ſaying, <hi>The Day is come, ſpoken of and foretold by the Prophet, of the pouring forth of God's Spirit upon all Fleſh, Sons and Daughters,</hi> &amp;c. And I exhorted them, both Prieſt and People, to take heed to a Meaſure or Manifeſtation thereof in their own Hearts, (and leave off their Idolatry) and come to be true Spiritual Worſhippers; and I laid before them the danger of the one, and the benefit of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; till the Prieſt cauſed me to be haled out; and when I came forth many of his Hearers followed me, and I had a good opportunity with them, and clear'd my ſelf to them, and left them. And as I was going away, I felt the ariſing of that Power that is worthy to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, and it was with me to go to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and when they came from their worſhip I met them, firſt the Mayor and his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, then the Lawyer and his, and after that the Prieſt, with many more; and I invited all to come to our Spiritual Worſhip, and I would engage that if any of them, young or old,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54975:36"/> male or female, had a Meſſage from the Lord to deliver there, that they ſhould have liberty, and not be abuſed, as the Prieſt cauſed me to be; for the Man that haled me out hurt my Arm, ſo that it was ſwelled ſome time after: and I told the Prieſt that he was not of the Primitive Faith and Church of Chriſt, teſtified of in Scripture; for there, if any thing was revealed to the Standers by or Hearers, they might ſpeak one by one; the firſt holding his peace; and he was ſilent before I ſpoke, and he ſaid I ſhould not have ſpoken in the Church; and I asked him what Church that was? for I had ſpoken in the true Church many times amongſt God's People, and they did not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me; and he ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke againſt a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſpeaking in the Church: I asked him what Woman that was, and what Church that was that ſhe ſhould not ſpeak in? and he did not anſwer me, but went away; and a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Friend that was with me took hold of him, and ſaid, My Friend, anſwer the Womans queſtion, (and the <hi>Dutch</hi> People were coming from their worſhip the while,) but the Prieſt put off his Hat to us and buſled away, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards endeavoured to ſend me to Priſon; but the God of Power (who preſerved me when much Evil hath been intended) prevented him, that he could not prevail with the Mayor, but he endeavoured to harm the Friends of that place after that I was gone: And after the <hi>firſt Day</hi> Meeting was over, I went the beginning of the Week to ſome other Meetings, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54975:37"/> came again a <hi>fourth Day,</hi> and God's Power was over all, and Friends had no harm; and we had another Heavenly Meeting, and ſo I came away and left Friends peaceable, and all was well, bleſſed be the Lord, and magnified be his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Power, over all, for evermore. <hi>Amen ſaith my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>I was informed that the Prieſt above ſpecified, did do his endeavour to ſtir up Perſecution against Friends, and put the Mayor to ſome trouble, for not puniſhing me; but therein he did, nor could do, no more than manifeſt his own Malice, and what Birth he was of: The Lord had ſet his Bounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. V.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>IN all this long Journey, this I can ſay, (to the Honour and Glory of my tender God, and to the Praiſe of his Providential Power,) and be it known to all, That altho' I had none to accompany me of my own or Friends pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding, yet the Lord ſo ordered it, that I had ſtill ſome honeſt Woman, or Maiden Friend, both by Sea &amp; Land. In the firſt Veſſel that ever I was in, I had an honeſt ancient maiden Friend, namely <hi>Sarah Yoaklet,</hi> who was my Companion from <hi>London</hi> until I came to <hi>Long-Iſland:</hi> And then in <hi>New-England,</hi> one <hi>Lydia Wright,</hi> another faithful Friend, was willing to travel with me, and did accompany me a conſiderable time; and ſtill the Lord ſo ordered it, that when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver one left me, that another was ready to take her place to be my Companion. And when I returned home, there came with me an ancient
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54975:37"/> Maiden Friend, who had been out in thoſe Countries in the ſervice of Truth ſix Years, whoſe name was <hi>Margaret Kerby;</hi> and on the 3d of the 4th Month, 1681, I arrived ſafely at <hi>Dover</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> where I was three Weeks in the ſervice of Truth: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that (bleſſed and renowned be the Holy Name of Jeſus) I came to <hi>London,</hi> and after a little time ſpent in viſiting Friends at <hi>London,</hi> I came ſafe home: And as I pondered weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and beheld the Preſervation of me and mine, and the manifold Mercies that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived when ſo far remote one from another, my Heart was truly tendered in the ſenſe of my Heavenly Father's Love, and my Soul mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the Preſerving and Delivering Power, and the cry run through me, <hi>Lord God of my Life, let me and mine never forget thy Goodneſs, for it is wonderfully to be admired; and thy unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible Love to be conſidered, by all thoſe unto whom it hath been ſo largely extended. And as I conſider our nothingneſs, and thy tenderneſs towards us, I cannot but abhor ſelf, and breath, unto thee, that I and mine may for ever hold ſelf in no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and follow Jeſus through the daily croſs; wherein I (through tender Mercy) have found pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when of my ſelf I could do nothing whereby to fulfil what was required of me, but ſelf was very ready to hinder me, as the ſelf-ſeeking Spirit is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thoſe that are not aware of it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſire, above all things, that I and mine, whom the Lord hath been ſo good unto, may be watchful; and, in order thereunto, I commit all</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:54975:38"/> 
               <hi>unto that God of Power that hath preſerved hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, and is able to keep and preſerve unto the end: To whom be all Glory and Praiſe for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter writen at</hi> Graveſend <hi>to Friends of the Womens Meeting, by</hi> J. V. <hi>when ſhe was going to Sea, for her long Journy. The 24th of the 12th Month,</hi> 1679.</head>
            <p>DEar and well-beloved Siſters, my Love and Life Salutes you; even in a ſenſe of the tender Love of my Heavenly Father do I embrace you, and greatly encourage you to keep your Womens Meetings, and keep up your Teſtimonies, every one in your places; for every one hath a Teſtimony for the Pure God, tho' not in Words, yet in the Word of Life, which hath quickened our Souls, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully operated thereon, even in our Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Meeting: Hath not the ſenſe of it been ſufficient to engage our Hearts to ſerve him; and to bare our faithful Teſtimony for him in Purity of Life and Converſation, that his Name may be honoured, and the precious Truth propagated? For this you know how long hath been the travail of my Soul amongſt you; and, I hope, it will be the travail of yours in my abſence, that if ever we ſee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Faces again, it may be with Joy and not with Sorrow. So let your Breathings be for my Welfare in the Lord Jeſus, as mine are for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54975:38"/> you; for had it not been to keep Covenant with my God, I could not have given up my weak Body to the Sea; but in my long and ſore Exerciſes, I often promiſed the Pure God, that I would give up my Life as a Sacrifice, if he would accept of it; and now he hath tried me, and if he pleaſe to take it, it is but my reaſonable ſervice to offer it up to him; but I did intend you ſhould have had more time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge of it, but that I could not tell whether it might have been taken of me; therefore I forbore ſpeaking of it publickly, till at length I could not come back; but now, in the univerſal Love of God, do I take my leave of you all, not knowing whether I may ſee you again or not. Remember my dear Love to the Brethren, whoſe Labour of Love and Work of Faith is for the Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the precious Truth.</p>
            <p>And the Lord God Eternal keep us all cloſe unto himſelf, in that which neither Sea nor Land can ſeparate; for in it my Love doth tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reach unto you all, being clear in the ſight of my God of all ſervice, ſave only this which my Life lies engaged for. Here I ſtand reſigned to live or die in the Will of my God, and ſo I deſire him to keep me to the end.</p>
            <p>And, dear Friends, be Valiant for the Truth, that it may not be undervalued through a cowardly creeping Libertine Spirit, for that hath done too much hurt already; ſtand over it, I beſeech you all, and quit your ſelves like
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54975:39"/> faithful Soldiers, fighting under the Banner of Love, which our tender God hath ſpread over us, that we may not be aſham'd to bear the Croſs; and take heed, leſt any cauſe the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Croſs to ceaſe, for ſuch are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Chriſt Jeſus, let them profeſs what they will; for there is no way to the Crown, but by and through the Croſs. So, in that which brings us into ſubjection, do I remain (preſent with you in Spirit, though abſent in Body,) your tender Siſter in the precious Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Graveſend,
<date>
                     <hi>the 24th of the 12th Month,</hi> 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Let this be read in your Womens Meeting, or any where, as a ſervice is ſeen.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter to her Husband,</hi> Richard Vokins, <hi>ſent from</hi> Road Iſland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Husband,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Love and Life ſalutes thee, with my dear Children, and my Father, and my brother <hi>O. S.</hi> and his Wife, and my Brother <hi>D</hi> and his Wife, and all the reſt of my dear Friends and Heavenly Relations, dearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54975:39"/> your Preſervation and Proſperity in the ever bleſſed Truth; and then I doubt not but our God will increaſe us in our outward ſtore. And, dear Heart, thou art often in my mind, and the breathing of my Life is for thee, as for my own Soul, and I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that all our Trials will work for good, if we love the Lord Jeſus as we ought to do: Thoſe Trials that we have had, and do now meet with, I hope will fit us for greater, and I do not know but I may come home again, to ſuffer with you, by the ſtrength of the ſame Power that hath preſerved us hitherto. Oh magnified be it for ever, ſaith my Soul, for it hath done for me great things. And, dear Heart, my ſervice is greater here than it was there, and I have pretty well clear'd my ſelf in <hi>Long Iſland,</hi> but at <hi>New-York</hi> I am not quite clear but I hope I ſhall ere long. I am now at <hi>Road-Iſland,</hi> going on to clear my ſelf as faſt as I may, as the Lord makes way for me. I intend to take the Meetings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this and <hi>Boston,</hi> and when I am clear there, I hope you may hear further from me, or ſee me, in ſome reaſonable time, as our tender God ſhall be pleaſed to order: And by this you may all know that my tender God is with me, and carries me through many ſore Exerciſes, and his mighty Power enables me to do his Service; and his Reward is not wanting, bleſſed be his Name, for all his tender Mercies. Friends are tender to me, and I am better in Health at preſent than I have been;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54975:40"/> but I have many Ailments attending my weak Body ſtill.</p>
            <p>So, dear Heart, let us breathe to our God together, though outwardly far aſunder, yet if it ſtands with the Will of our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may ſee one another again, to his Honour and our Comfort; and let us pray unto him, Day and Night, that we may be content, to be at his diſpoſe in Life or Death, together or aſunder, that he may be honoured, and our Souls comforted.</p>
            <p>And, dear Heart, remember to have an Eye over our dear Children, that they loſe not the ſenſe of Truth, which my Soul hath ſo deeply travailled for, when I was with them; for it is my fear, now I am from them, that if thou do not ſupply my place in my abſence, that the Spirit of this World will prevail, and hinder the Work of the Lord in their Hearts, and in thine too, and that will be to all our Sorrow. The Lord God Eternal keep us faithful to him unto the end, that we bare our Teſtimonies for his Truth with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at all times, and in all places, that we may not be aſham'd to confeſs him before Men if we ſhould come to be tried for our Lives; for it's a precious advancement to be a worthy Sufferer; and if the Mighty God do bring me home again, to partake of Suffering in my Native Land, I hope thoſe Exerciſes that I now go through will ſtill ſit me for greater; and I hope this is the end for which thee and I am tried. And ſo,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54975:40"/> in the Love of that which is able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us, do I once more ſalute thee, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy true and tender Wife, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Road-Iſland,
<date>
                     <hi>the 14th of the 4th Month,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>REmember my dear Love to my Children, and bid them mind the Lord, and to all Friends of our Meeting, and let my Son <hi>R.</hi> tell them that I greatly deſire their Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and I hope he will have an honeſt Teſtimony for God; and I would have <hi>Mary</hi> ſee this Letter, that ſhe may be of a believing Heart, that if the Lord ſhould bring us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether again, it may be to his Honour, and our great Comfort; the Lord is as well able to preſerve me home; as he was hither, and I hope he will in his time, I muſt leave that to him, and ſo I hope will you; for if we be not contented with his Will, it will not be well with us: And therefore let's learn <hi>Paul</hi>'s Leſſon, for we have great need in every ſtate to be content. No more, but dear Love, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in haſte,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. V.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:54975:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> Oliver Sanſom <hi>and his Wife.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Brother and Siſter,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHom I dearly love in the Lord Jeſus, (our Life) who makes hard things eaſie, bitter things ſweet, and bares up in the greateſt Trials, do I ſalute you, with my <hi>Mary,</hi> my Siſter <hi>Margery,</hi> and the reſt of them, earneſtly deſiring your Proſperity eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, as for my own Soul. And by this you may know, that tho' fore Exerciſes and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels attend on every hand; yet I am alive to magnifie that Power that hath preſerved in Dangers great, and Difficulties many, and is able to Preſerve unto the end, and therefore I deſire that we may truſt in it, and obey it, to the honour of it; for it hath been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in my weak Body, to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of many of the upright in Heart, and they are very Loving to me where ever I come: And my tender Father hath ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to do his Service in <hi>Long-Iſland,</hi> and <hi>New-York,</hi> and in <hi>Road-Iſland,</hi> and <hi>Boston,</hi> and <hi>New-Jerſey,</hi> and thoſe parts of <hi>America,</hi> and I was in hope to have come home when I was clear of <hi>New England;</hi> but the Lord hath laid it upon me to go to <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and in his Strength I am going on in a Veſſel that one <hi>George Fletcher</hi> is Owner and Maſter of, who profeſſes Truth. Do you not think
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54975:41"/> that a Line from you would be very precious to me? I neither heard from, nor ſaw one of my Native Land ſince I left it; but I cannot blame you, not knowing whither to direct it. Remember my dear Love to all dear Friends of our Mens and Womens Meetings, earneſtly deſiring their Faithfulneſs therein, and in all things elſe that pertains to the life of Truth, that we may bear our Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies in Uprightneſs unto the end, that in the end God may be glorified, and our Souls comforted, for ever and evermore. Dear <hi>Anne Lawrence</hi>'s Children be in my Mind as well as my own: I hope you will look after them in my Abſence, that we may have comfort of their Growth in the Truth, if ever we are preſent again; and if they grow in the Truth, and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and Love of God, then will the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of your tender Siſter be anſwered. And ſo in that which ſatisfies our Breathings, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Tender Sister, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>The 1ſt of the Eighth Month,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:54975:42"/>
            <head>
               <hi>For Friends at</hi> Graveſend <hi>in</hi> Long-Iſland, <hi>and elſe-where.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Love and Life ſalutes you, and in that which unites unto our God and endears us in the Heavenly Relation, you are often in my Remembrance; and my Souls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is that we may feel each other in a living growth, in that Life and Love of God which reaches over Sea and Land, and ſatisfies our Souls, and cauſes us to rejoyce together in Spirit, as preſent (though abſent in Body) joyning in the God of our ſweet Salvation; though in this World we meet with many bitter Exerciſes; yet bleſſed be his holy Name, his ſweet Salvation out-ballances all; and as in the Light we behold it, we have great cauſe to magnifie that Name that bringeth it: For there is power to make the Weak ſtrong, and to eſtabliſh the Feeble-minded; and we have ſufficiently partaken of its Preſervation and Deliverance. Glory and Honour and Praiſes over all be returned thereunto, our Souls have cauſe to ſay, for all his Mercies and great Loving Kindneſs, both Spiritual and Temporal; for his wonted Favours and renewings of Mercies daily. Who can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, and not be bowed into Tenderneſs before him? The conſideration thereof melts my Heart even at this time. And the breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Soul is to the God of my Life, that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54975:42"/> we may all keep low in the Valley of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Love, where the Well-ſpring of Life doth overflow; that our Souls through its ſweet Refreſhings may live unto him, that through its ariſing we may magnifie his Name and celebrate his Praiſes, for Death and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot. And therefore we had need be all watching in the Light, and waiting for the ariſings of Life, that Death and Darkneſs may be ſubdued out of our Families, and out of our Aſſemblies; that our Families may be ſeaſoned with the Heart-cleanſing and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving holy Fear, that they may be of God's Families, and our Aſſemblies crown'd with Life; that Truth may be promoted thereby in our Generation, and our Poſterity bleſſed in the Generations to come. For this end the Lord hath taken Compaſſion on us, and raiſed us up of all the Families of the Earth; and if we do not anſwer the requirings of his Love, he may lay us by, and raiſe up whom he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>Oh! dear Hearts feel his Love, for it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Love my Soul can truly ſay. Oh! what manner of Love is this (as one ſaid in his day) that he hath Loved us with, that when we were afar off and Strangers to him, he made known his precious Truth unto us, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed a meaſure thereof in us, to help our Infirmities and to teach us, when we could find no comfort of all the Teachings of the Idol Shepherds, nor no help for our Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: Oh how precious was his voice, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54975:43"/> comely was his Countenance, and how tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly were our Hearts affected therewith, in the day of our Convincement! Oh it was a day of Love never to be forgotten! And how hath he ſurrounded us by his Power ever ſince? Surely his Fatherly Love hath been and is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to oblige us to Obedience; for he is not wanting to his tender Seed, but is appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Affliction of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and to work Deliverance for <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to relieve the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Seed, in the remote corners of the Earth. There are many going and gone out of <hi>Old England</hi> to <hi>Penſilvania</hi> and <hi>New Jarſey,</hi> that have been as Inſtruments in the Hand of the Lord for the promoting his Truth here; and I hope they will be ſo there, to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his great Name and the Comfort of his Children in the Neighbouring <hi>Iſlands;</hi> for the Lord will exalt his Truth, though the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed grow worſe and worſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore let our Hearts magnifie his Name, and our Souls (and all that is within us) return Praiſes and Thankſgiving unto him, for he is worthy, who is God bleſſed for ever, and evermore, <hi>Amen,</hi> ſaith my Soul, who am a Traveller in Spirit for the tender Seed, and a Rejoycer in its Proſperity,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joan Vokins.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>This Epiſtle its ſuppoſed was Written ſoon after her return home.</p>
            </argument>
            <trailer>Let this Epiſtle be Copied and ſent to <hi>Matinicoke,</hi> to <hi>M. Pryer</hi> and Friends thereaway, to be read among them.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <opener>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:54975:43"/> Here follows the Copies of ſome more Letters that ſhe wrote and ſent when ſhe was in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica.</hi>
            </opener>
            <head>
               <hi>To her Husband and Children, the 11th of the 11th Month,</hi> 1680. <hi>from</hi> Nevice.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Husband and Children,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY endeared Love, in the Love of my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, doth dearly ſalute you, and the breathing of my Soul is unto my tender God, that you may be faithful and obedient to your Meaſures received, that you may grow in the Knowledge and Love of God, and of his Son Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>whom to know is Eternal Life,</hi> which is better than Natural Life, or any thing that thereunto belongeth: Oh, dear Hearts, conſider of it, and forget not the goodneſs of the Lord; for unutterable is his Love towards us: My Heart is tendered in the feeling of it, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forget his tender dealing with us; and the cry runs often through me to the God of my Life, That you may not forget his Goodneſs, nor ſlight his tender Love, nor neglect your Duties to him; for, dear Hearts, he is not an hard Maſter, but his Reward is ſufficient to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our Hearts to his Service; Therefore let our Hearts be encouraged to continue in well-doing, and to watch againſt the Enemy, that he may not prevail to draw out your Minds from waiting upon the Lord: Surely there is great danger does attend you, my dear and tender
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54975:44"/> ones. Oh let your Hearts be diligent to ſeek the Honour of God, and the Exaltation of his Truth above all things; then I ſhall have the deſire of my Soul anſwered: For I am greatly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for you, and my Prayers are for you Night and Day, that your Souls may live to God, whatever your Bodies endure: But for your comfort, I put you in mind of the ſweet Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of him that ſaid, <hi>Firſt ſeek the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Righteouſneſs thereof, and all things elſe ſhall be added:</hi> And I am truly ſatisfied, he is never failing to fulfil his ſweet Promiſes unto them that <hi>keep his Commandments;</hi> and if we love him, let it be manifeſt by our keeping his Commands; for <hi>he is worthy to be feared,</hi> and truſted in, and depended upon, and had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance continually. <hi>The Lord God of my Life ſtay your Minds, that you may wait upon him, that in his own time, and upon his own terms you may partake of the fulfilling of his ſweet Promiſes, which are attained unto by loving the Light, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Life of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo, dear Hearts, let us be ſingly reſigned unto our God; for I can truly ſay, his Love is moſt deeply of an engaging Nature; for by it I have been preſerved from great Dangers, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils by Sea, and Perils by Land, and Perils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt falſe Brethren; but out of them all his mighty Power delivered me, and I am yet alive to magnifie it, Glory, and Honour, and Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Praiſes be unto his Name for evermore, ſaith my Soul; for he daily filleth my Heart therewith, and makes me able to do his Service
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54975:44"/> beyond Expectation; and he is not wanting to communicate to my Soul (Glory to his worthy Name), but his Reward is in my Boſom, which glads my Heart, and refreſhes my Soul, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds my weak Body, that I am not without hopes of ſeeing you again; for I have cauſe to ſay, <hi>There is nothing impoſſible unto my God.</hi> I have been moſt of this Winter upon the roaring Seas, Two Months at a time, and ſaw no Land, and my Clothes were not off Two Nights all that time, ſo far as I can remember, and there was no conveniency for my weak Body: There were <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and I had fore Exerciſes amongſt them, both inwardly and outwardly; but yet I had good Service alſo amongſt them, and they did confeſs to the Power of my God. And altho they were moſt of them very wicked, yet they were chained by it, and the Paſſengers were kind to me for the Truth's ſake; and when it pleaſed the Lord to bring us to Land, we arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the Iſland of <hi>Antego,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> and there I found a precious People, and had Two Meetings a Day for a Week, with <hi>White People</hi> and <hi>Blacks;</hi> and on the <hi>7th</hi> Day is their <hi>Childrens Meetings,</hi> and they have alſo <hi>Mens and Womens Meetings,</hi> and the Goſpel-Order is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and eſtabliſhing in thoſe remote Iſlands, Glory to God for ever. And they teach their Children <hi>G. F</hi>'s Catechiſm. And we went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board the Ship again, deſigning for <hi>Barbadoes;</hi> but that ſmall Veſſel was ſo heavy laden, that we could not get from the <hi>West Indies,</hi> but kept
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54975:45"/> up and down another Month, that the Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were all weary; for Water grew ſcarce and ſtinking, and I was very weak: And when we came to another Iſland, we that were Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers were willing to go a-ſhoar; but the Veſſel did not enter there; and then my Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe was very great; for I had great drawings to go there, and then the Weight of my Service there, remained with me: And a few Days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we bore up, and went to another Iſland, where there was no <hi>Friends,</hi> and there I went a-ſhore, and ſome of the other Paſſengers, and I knew no perſon there; the Inhabitants were moſt part <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and I was almoſt ſpent when I came there; but the Lord was exceeding good, and comforted me every way, and I got a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage back again to <hi>Antego;</hi> and it remained with me to go to the Iſland of <hi>Nevice,</hi> and I could not be clear of the Weight of it; and when I had been ſweetly refreſhed, through the Love of my God, amongſt them again at <hi>Antego,</hi> way was made for me to go from thence to <hi>Nevice,</hi> and an honeſt Widow went along with me, who was very helpful to me; and we had good Service amongſt the <hi>Blacks</hi> and <hi>Whites;</hi> and ſhe remembers her Love to you all, and her Prayers are with mine unto the Lord for you: And now we are clear of <hi>Nevice,</hi> and going again to <hi>Antego,</hi> and do hope the Lord will make way for me to be at <hi>Barbadoes</hi> ere long; for I do underſtand it is but a Weeks Sail or Two at moſt, if the Wind ſit fair. When we came from <hi>New York,</hi> they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54975:45"/> ſpoke of but Three or Four Weeks Voyage to <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and we came out thence about the time called <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> and I have not ſeen it yet: I ſent you many Letters from thence when I came away, by which you may know my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in <hi>New England,</hi> and the time when I came away from thence. I do not know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you received any of my Letters, but I have taken all opportunities I could, both by Sea and Land, to ſend. I met with a Veſſel up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sea the laſt Letter that I ſent, and ſhe was bound for <hi>London.</hi> I do long to hear of your Welfare, but I do not blame you that I receive no Lines, except you could tell whither to direct them. I have not ſeen one of my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Land, that I knew, ſince I came forth: But the Lord is with me, and unto his preſerving Power I commit you, with my ſelf, and all the tender ones, that <hi>Amalek</hi>'s Spirit may not hurt the hinder part of the Flock, nor turn the weak out of the way.</p>
            <p>Dear Hearts, let's be ſingle unto God, that our Underſtandings may be opened, and kept open, that no ſubtle Spirit may betray our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency: And let us never forget the Watch; and if we fulfil that Command, God will be honoured, and our Souls comforted for ever and for ever, and for evermore. Forget not your Family-Meeting on Firſt Days at Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; let not any thing hinder.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written in the Iſland of</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<date>
                     <hi>the 11th of the 11th Month,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:54975:46"/>
            <head>
               <hi>And in the ſame Letter there were a few Lines add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her Son</hi> Thomas Vokins, <hi>being then an Apprentice with</hi> William Gibſon, <hi>in</hi> London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Dear Son</hi> T. V.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Love ſalutes thee, and thy dear Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Miſtriſs, and all the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus, earneſtly deſiring your Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare as my own. And dear Heart, let thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Endeavours anſwer the Deſires of my Heart; for my Soul's breathing is, that thou maiſt be kept low and chaſte, that thou maiſt fear at all times; that thou maiſt do as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did, that could not ſin againſt his God. Oh dear Son, it is a precious thing to feel the Awe of the Lord upon thy Heart: Oh that this may be thy State, that thou maiſt be found watching unto Prayer, and continue in the ſame, that thou maiſt witneſs Preſervation from all the Enemies Snares, and that thy Mind may be ſtayed in the Light, to wait for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of Life; that thou maiſt live to God, and ſeek his Kingdom, <hi>and the righteouſneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> and then thou need'ſt not fear but <hi>all things elſe will be added.</hi> And I hope thy Diligence and Faithfulneſs to God, and unto thy Maſter and Miſtriſs, will increaſe their Love to thee. So hoping thou wilt take good Counſel, and bring forth the Fruit thereof, to the Honour of our precious God, and to all our Comforts.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>This is from thy tender Mother,</hi> J. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:54975:46"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Epiſtle to Friends of</hi> New York, <hi>and there-away.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear and well-beloved Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Lines are left to your weighty Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in this Seaſon, whilſt opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity doth preſent; for Times and Seaſons are in our Father's Hand, and we know not how ſoon he may put a period to our days: and therefore we are all concerned to ſeek the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the precious Truth, whoſe Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency far exceeds the pureſt Gold, and the Gain thereof far tranſcendeth all earthly Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Oh let it be our greateſt care to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with it, that we may ſay with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, in a living ſenſe thereof, That Godlineſs with contentment is the greateſt Gain: for we right well know, that no other Gain is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for our everlaſting welfare; neither will any thing elſe ſtand us inſtead, when our God calls for an Account of our Talents; and therefore let it be the bent of our Hearts; and the inclinations of our Minds to improve them, that we may give our Account with joy; that our God may be honoured, and our Souls comforted, when this momentary Pilgrimage ſhall be ended, and all our Troubles and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes forgotten: where the fulneſs of that which we have already the earneſt of; being an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred-fold better than any thing we have parted
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54975:47"/> with for it: and if we ſhould be yet tried to part with all, even Life and all, it's but our reaſonable Service to give it up all to him from whom we have received it: for what have we (that is good,) but what we have received of him, and what is it that he is not worthy of? Is not his Love ſufficient to engage our hearts to his Service? Have he not delivered us in Dangers deep, and Difficulties great, and brought us through many and ſore Diſtreſſes? And hath he not made us Partakers of many precious Promiſes? Endleſs Praiſes be to his moſt holy Name, ſaith my Soul. The feeling of his ſweet refreſhing Life that he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to my Soul, is a hundred-fold better than Husband and Children, or any other outward Mercies that he hath made me partaker of, though very near and dear unto me.</p>
            <p>And now dear Friends the Scriptures are a fulfilling in us; therefore let our earneſt that we have received, engage our hearts to our Maſter's work, that we may receive the fulneſs of that which we already have an earneſt of, for we have not a hard Maſter to ſerve: but behold he comes, and his reward is with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh let's wait for him to enlarge our hearts more and more, then ſhall we love to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate his Truth, and run the way of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments with joy and great delight, that we may all witneſs the fulfilling of that ſweet Promiſe of a hundred-fold in this life, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the great and double reward of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54975:47"/> Faithful, which is the joy of the Soul in the Life which is everlaſting.</p>
            <p>And ſo, dear Friends, let us all keep a narrow watch over our hearts, that the Spirit of this World do not creep in, to draw the Mind from that which did at firſt convince us; for that is as precious as ever, and never waxes old; and therefore let our zeal for it never wax cold: but let us prize all opportunities to aſſemble together, that we may feel our hearts enclin'd, ſingly to wait, that we may receive a further diſpenſation of life, that a growing People we may be; that love unto our God, and unto one another may abound amongſt us; that the Way of our God may not ſeem unpleaſant, nor his Commands grievous unto any of us; neither that given way unto which would lead into the liberty of the fleſh again, for that is a dividing Spirit, that will ſeparate from God, and uncement and break the Unity of the Body: it is of a creeping nature, and enmity lodges in it, whatever it may pretend; and becauſe it hath already wrought in a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and brought diſhonour to the worthy Name of our God, and reproach upon the precious Truth: Therefore it doth deeply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us to double our diligence in doing our Duties to honour him, in the propagating of the Truth.</p>
            <p>Oh Friends, let us for ever have this before the view of our Minds, let no other beloved hinder: for if we love any thing more than
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54975:48"/> this, it will not go well with us; for our God will ſearch the Camp, and if there be a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh</hi> Garment, or a Wedge of never ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Gold, yet if the Work of the Lord be hindered thereby, his Wrath will ſurely come upon it and conſume it: for a clean Camp the Lord will make, that his Truth may be renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the day of purifying is come and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming more, in which the Hypocrites ſhall be tryed, and the upright in heart comforted, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there may be many that were firſt, come to be laſt, and ſome <hi>Judas-like</hi> betray their Maſter; yet the Lord will ſpread his Truth in the Nations, and magnifie his own Power, by ſtaining the glory of all fleſh, and by laying Self low before him, that it may be had in no reputation: for he will not give his glory unto another, the Adulterer, nor the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolater ſhall not be decked with his Jewels: for where Self is decked, the Lord is provoked: but where Self is denied, and the daily Croſs taken up, there the low appearance of the Son of God is bowed unto, which ſeems contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto them, who cauſes the offence of the Croſs to ceaſe, and ſettles upon their Lees, and ſits down in a ſtate of careleſneſs, thinking themſelves ſecure, without the performance of their Duty, in Obedience to the meaſure of Truth received, that ſhould bring into a Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's ſtate: Oh Friends, we all know, that reſt is polluted, let us all up and be doing, that our Lamps may be trimmed, and we all may be ready
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54975:48"/> to meet the Bridegroom of our Souls, that we may enter in while the Door is open: but if we delay until the Door is ſhut, then it will be in vain to ſeek, we ſhall not be able to enter, when the Door is ſhut againſt us: then what will the profeſſion of Truth do for us.</p>
            <p>Therefore let us with one heart and mind labour together, and let our breathings be one for another, that the poſſeſſion of Life may be more and more inherited amongſt us, that we may be refreſhed one in another, when toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or aſunder, that a ſympathizing one with another, we may have, as Members of one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to the honour of Chriſt our holy Head, from whom we receive nouriſhment, to keep us from withering, and to make us to grow and be uſeful all in our meaſures, that one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay unto another, I have no need of thee: for if we are cemented together as Members of one Body, we muſt needs be all concerned for the honour of our Head, and the comfort of one another, I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unfeigned Friend in the precious unchangeable Truth: <hi>JOAN VOKINS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>This to be read amongst Friends at</hi> New York, <hi>(or elſe-where) as in the Wiſdom of God it may be ſeen meet.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:54975:49"/>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Written in the Iſland of <hi>Antegua</hi> in the Movings of the Spirit of Truth, and in the ſence which that gave me of the ſtate of Friends there.</dateline>
                  <signed>J. V.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Here follows a LETTER that ſhe wrote on Board the firſt Veſſel going for</hi> Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica; <hi>directed, and ſent to ſome Women-Friends in</hi> London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Cannot forget your labour of love, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly care concerning me, and do return the acknowledgment thereof, with kind ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance; and this is to certifie you, that after I left old <hi>England,</hi> I had no cauſe of doubt or fear: but the roaring Sea is to me as the dry Land, becauſe of my heavenly Father's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and power, which do make hard things eaſie, and bitter things ſweet, in whoſe Arms we are preſerved hitherto, and we have great cauſe to hope we ſhall unto the end: for he is with us, and have done for me already, more then I did expect from his tender hand: I have not had one fit ſince I came aboard: but <hi>Sarah</hi> and I are both Sea-ſick: but we have good encouragement in our Voyage; and here is ſome Friends, and ſome other ſober People, and I have good Service amongſt them; and the Peace of my God flows in as a River, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54975:49"/> his Love and Life as a mighty Stream, which I would not be ſeparated from, for all that is in Old <hi>England:</hi> and let all Friends know, that ask concerning me, that its very well with my Soul; Glory everlaſting be unto my tender God for ever. Though my Body is weak, yet he that made it, is worthy to have the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it: and unto him it is reſigned; for he hath often brought it down, and rais'd it up: and can do with it as he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>And let my dear Husband and Friends thereaway know, that I am at home with my God; though abſent from my outward: and he that cloaths the Lillies, and feeds the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, takes care of me as well here, as at home; and as to my bodily weakneſs, I am not worſe than I was at home: but much eaſier in my Mind. Bleſſed and magnified be the Name of the Lord for ever.</p>
            <p>It is troubleſome for me to write, the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel doth ſo wave. I deſire that <hi>Suſan Dew,</hi> and <hi>Mary Elſon</hi> may ſee this, or have a Copy of it: and alſo my dear Husband and Children, to whom my indeared Love is recommended, and to all our Friends there-away, that loves the Truth, and walks in it; for they can ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathize with me, and are partakers of the reward of life with me in our own Boſoms: which is and hath been more to me, ſince I have been aboard the Veſſel, than my natural Life: and it's the beſt Cordial that I can ever
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54975:50"/> have; for healing vertue is in it, by which my Soul and weak Body is ſtrengthened and comforted in times of great weakneſs, fore tryals and exerciſes, in the ſenſe of which my Soul is tendered before the God of my life: not queſtioning but that we may ſee one anothers faces again with joy, and not with ſorrow: and yet if we do not ſee face to face; yet if we abide together in Spirit in the work and ſervice of our God, then ſhall he be honoured, and our Souls comforted, and ſo ſhall I have the deſire of my Soul an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; who am a Traveller for the tender Seed ſake, in the ſervice of Truth, wherein I greet you all in the ſalutation of my dear love, and therein do take my leave, and bid you farewel in the Lord JESUS, remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true and unfeigned Friend and Siſter in the precious Truth, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From on Ship-board in the <hi>Downs,</hi>
                  <date>27th of the 12th Month, 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:54975:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Epiſtle to Friends in</hi> Rhode-Iſland, <hi>and there-away.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Love and Life ſalutes you all that loves the precious Truth, and lives in it; for they are very dear and near one unto another, even as Epiſtles written in one anothers Hearts that cannot be forgotten; not written with Ink or Pen, but with the uniting and healing Spirit, that unites us unto our God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dears us one unto another, in which I am one with you in Tryals and Exerciſes, and the breathing of my Soul is unto the God of our lives that all may be cut off that troubles you; and that Love and Life, and all other Spiritual Graces and Gifts may be multiplied and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in and amongſt you, that you may perſevere as the Worthies of the Lord, that through renewings of the right Spirit you may be more and more Conquerours over all that is wrong: for our God is on his way, Glory to his Name for ever, and he hath regard to the very hindermoſt of the Flock; therefore let all put on Valour and Courage to follow the Lamb, for he is on his way Triumphantly; and he and his faithful Followers ſhall have the Victory, though we may meet with much by the way, yet we have great encouragement ſtill to look to him who have hitherto preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54975:51"/> in dangers deep and difficult; and though in this World we meet with many Troubles, yet our Helper is nigh, yea, a God at hand to deliver out of them all. Surely his love is ſufficient to engage our Hearts to his Service; for we have every one a Service for our tender God in our places, and purity of Life and Converſation is that which will anſwer to the eſtabliſhing and confirming of all that keeps thereunto: though the outward appearance of things may make ſome weak ones to reaſon and queſtion, and be ready to ſtumble, yet the Goſpel-light and life, and the good order thereof is very comfortable, and as it is kept unto will reſolve all doubts, and ſtop the dark reaſoner, and put a period to all unprofitable Controverſies, which things the Lord grant may be brought to paſs amongſt you, and in all the Churches, to the Honour and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Holy Name and Precious Truth, and the comforting and building up and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of every breathing tender Babe, that he over all may have the praiſe, and our Souls the comfort for evermore, <hi>Amen,</hi> Saith your Friend in the unchangeable Truth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Barbadoes,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>6th.</hi> of the firſt Month, 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let this be read among Friends in</hi> Rhode-Iſland, <hi>as the Wiſdom of God ſhall direct.</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:54975:51"/> Here are at the <hi>Weſt-India Iſlands</hi> a very good Preſident concerning Children, and I could wiſh that it were ſo among the Lord's People every where. Friends Children meet together once a week, and ſit together with their Parents, and wait upon the Lord, and are Inſtructed, and they learn dear <hi>G. F</hi>'s Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm at home, <hi>[and then they ſay it at the Meeting once a week]</hi> and I do believe that it do produce a good Effect, and I can truly ſay, that the Power of the Almighty is amongſt them, for many of them was tendered and let Tears when I was at their Meeting, and Friends were refreſhed. Here in <hi>Barbadoes</hi> are Family Meetings ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frequently and comfortable.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>An Epiſtle to Friends in</hi> Eaſt-Jerſey.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BE of believing Hearts, and keep to the meaſure of Light already received, that none may be vailed in their Underſtandings, and ſo come to loſs; but that all may have the benefit of their own meaſures, that we may Magnifie our God together; for in the feeling of that Spirit that helpeth our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and teaches us, we are greatly encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to travel on, though there is much to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54975:52"/> be met with by the way. Oh therefore let none be weary in well-doing, but all to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, that God's Plantation may flouriſh in every Heart, that he may have the Fruit to his Glory, for he is making manifeſt his great love to his tender Seed in thoſe remote corners of the Earth; and he will make his Power known, and his Goſpel-light is ſhining, and he will multiply his Mercies, and increaſe his Bleſſings, both Spiritually and Temporally, unto thoſe who live the Goſpel-life, and keep to its bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Order: Oh the great love and tender deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our God, that he is viſiting thoſe Iſlands, which cauſes my Soul often to rejoyce; for he have heard the Cry of the poor, and is ariſen for the help of the needy, and have made many willing to leave their Native Land, that are as Inſtruments in his hand, for to build up in the pure victorious Faith, which have long been the breathing of my Soul for you; and for the Seed ſake I have been concerned cloſe with the God of my Life, and the cry in me hath often been unto him to ſend forth more faithful Labourers amongſt you, that his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard may be dreſſed and cleanſed from all that hindreth its growth, and he hath heard, and anſwered in meaſure, bleſſed be his Name. Oh Friends, let every one be concerned, and none to be idle, but all to the work of the Day, leſt Night come and prevent you.</p>
            <p>For now is the day ſpringing from on High viſiting you, and the affliction of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54975:52"/> the troubles of <hi>Jacob</hi> the Lord have removed, and for his Seed ſake will yet more appear and work its deliverance in the hearts of all that are truly tender of it: although the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent is very ſubtil and buſie, and always try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to betray Innocency; yet the Watch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept, he is prevented, and our Souls pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Therefore, dear Friends, let us not forget that Command, leſt the Enemy ſhould prevail. Oh feel a neceſſity of watchfulneſs, that we may keep our hearts diligently; that we may feel the iſſues of Life, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man may grow and be capable to act for God; for we have every one, both Male and Female, a Service in our proper places; and them that are diligent in doing their Duty, ſhall be ſure of a bleſſed Reward of Life and Peace: therefore let all be encouraged that are poor and needy, and feeble-minded; Oh let them put on Courage, yea, the very hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of the Flock; for our Captain is coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, he goes on Conquering and to Conquer victoriouſly, and by his Power he brings great things to paſs, and is working deliverance for his ſuffering Seed, that have breathed to him in ſecret, and could not be ſatisfied, but was without all hope of help, until the ancient Power was brought to light, and the Spirit of Truth revealed, to help our Infirmities, and to teach us to depart from Iniquity, and to do the things that is well pleaſing unto our God. Oh the day of our convincement! in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54975:53"/> which our hearts and ſouls were tendered, and we made ſenſible of our ſtates, is never to be forgotten; but the Ancient Power that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered us then, to be kept unto, that we may do the work of the day; for the Goſpel-day calls for purity of Life to adorn it. Oh that we may be, as <hi>John</hi> ſaid, fearing God, and giving glory to him, for the hour of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come; and we and ours ought to fear him, and ſtand in his awe, and not ſin againſt him. Oh that we above all things may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour that our Families may be of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and our Aſſemblies crown'd with life, that living Sacrifices may be offered in our Spiritual Worſhip: for broken hearts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ſpirits, our tender God will never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe.</p>
            <p>And therefore, dear Friends, let us keep low in the Valley of our Father's love, where the Well ſprings of Life do flow, that a living Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple we may be, to the praiſe of our God, and the promoting of Truth in Generations to come, that our Off-ſpring may be encouraged by our good Examples, ſucceſſively to honour Truth when we are gone to our Reſt, that our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity may be bleſſed of the Lord, and be to his praiſe, and our everlaſting comfort for ever and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Barbadoes</hi> in
<date>the firſt Month, 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:54975:53"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Epiſtle to ſome Friends in</hi> New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>but it hath reſpect to the general ſtate of Friends there.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>T. and Ann Potter,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DEar Friends, my Love do truly reach to you and your Children, deſiring your welfare every way, even as for my own, not forgetting your love to me when I was there, but in a ſenſe of that love that our God have ſhed abroad in our hearts, do I ſalute you, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſiring that our Children may be his Children, and that they and we may magnifie his power together, though outwardly far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder. Oh that we and ours may truly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after this: for its the breathing of my Soul that we may feel one another in harmleſs hearts, that we may breath one for another, and be refreſhed one in another, though ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in body, yet preſent in ſpirit, ſerving our God, and eying him that he may direct our hearts, and keep our minds ſtaid, that when the winds do blow, and the ſtorms do beat, we may be upon a ſure foundation: for all foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations ſhall be tried, and the ſandy buildings will not ſtand in the trying times: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we had need be builders up of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our moſt holy faith, that we may be firmly eſtabliſhed, and as good ſouldiers endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hardſhips unto the end; for our Captain
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54975:54"/> is on his way, Glory to his worthy Name, and he goes on triumphantly conquering, and to conquer, and he and his faithful Followers ſhall have the Victory, and his love is ſufficient to encourage the feeble ones, for by his power we have been preſerved in dangers many, and very great and difficult; and he hath been a preſent help in the times of our greateſt need, and though we have in our travel here, met with many troubles, yet he (who is our God at hand) delivers out of all. Everlaſting Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be unto his Name for ever: he hath made known the ſpiritual Armour. Oh that we may rightly prove it, that the Strong-holds of Sin and Satan may be pulled down, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Holineſs ſet up in the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that our God may be honoured, and his Truth exalted, and his Children comforted for ever and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mind my dear love to <hi>Elizabeth Hooten,</hi> and to the Friend and her Husband, (that went with me to <hi>West Jerſey)</hi> and to <hi>William Aſton</hi> and his Wife, and <hi>Tho. Leeds</hi> and his Wife, and let them know that I ſhould be glad to hear, that a Meeting were ſetled at <hi>Middleton;</hi> and mind my love to <hi>S. Cooper,</hi> and his Wife and Family, and let them and other Friends know, that I believe there would be great Service in eſtabliſhing a Meeting there; my love to <hi>R. Lippingcot, William Shaddock,</hi> and the Friend <hi>Warner,</hi> and to all the reſt of Friends;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54975:54"/> for my love is truly to them all, as if I nam'd them and their Wives one by one. And my ſervent deſire is, that the precious Truth may proſper amongſt you: and that faith and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and love and life, and all other ſpiritual graces and gifts, may abound amongſt you: and that all that is wrong may be purged out. Oh that all of you would wait to feel the renewings of the right Spirit, that there might be no room in the heart, to entertain the wrong Spirit, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or hurt innocency.</p>
            <p>And the Lord God of my Life diſcover its ſubtilty, and keep us all upon our watch, that none of us may be taken in his ſnares, for they are many and dangerous: and therefore I commit you with my ſelf, and all that loves the Truth, and lives in it, to the never-failing God, who is worthy to be feared and obeyed, truſted in, and depended upon by us, and all that love him, for ever and for evermore.</p>
            <p>You would ſay, that I have great cauſe ſo to declare, if you did but know what he has brought me through, ſince I left you: but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be his Name, he enabled me to do his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice every-where; and Friends are kind and loving to me here at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and ſo they were at the <hi>Leeward</hi> Iſlands. No more, but unfeigned Love; and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend and Siſter in the precious Truth,</hi> Joan Vokins.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Barbadoes,</hi>
                  <date>14th of the 1ſt Month, 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:54975:55"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Friends in</hi> Weſt Jerſey.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>WIlliam Peachee,</hi> after the Salutation of my Love to Thee and thy Wife and Friends, This is to let thee and Friends there know, that I cannot forget you: but the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel of my Soul is for you: and the tender God of my Life has heard the Cry of his oppreſſed Seed, and arriſen and will appear more and more for its deliverance, although the <hi>Philiſtine</hi> Spirit do ſtrongly ſtrive, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maleck</hi> lay by the way: yet <hi>Iſrael</hi> is greatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and have great cauſe to travel on, for the Captain of our Salvation is going on before us conquering and to conquer: and he will gather his Sons from far, and his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the ends of the Earth; and for this end he viſits the Dark Corners, and for his Seed ſake he has appeared on your behalf, and if you mind the Goſpel-light, and live the Goſpel-life, and keep the Goſpel-order, then will God's Plantation grow, and bring forth Fruit to his praiſe, and then you may expect his Bleſſings and Proſperity upon you and yours: but if you ſlight the great Love of God, and let in the Spirit of this World and get you other Lovers, that will greatly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord, and cauſe him to withhold his Mercies from you, and cauſe you to fail of your expectations. This loving Caution ſprung
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54975:55"/> in my Heart unto you, and in that which thinks no evil I leave it with you, hoping that in the ſame you will receive it, that in the reading our Lives may be refreſhed together, though in Perſon far aſunder: for it is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing precious to me, and my life rejoyces at the feeling of a living Brother or Siſters growth in the truth, and it's that my Soul travels for, who am a friend to it, and as I feed with you in the Land of the Living, we can ſing together as the ranſomed of the Lord; and the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of my Soul is, that all that are there may be preſerved, and that many thouſands more may be gathered to the Honour of his great and worthy Name and our mutual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, for ever and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Barbadoes,
<date>
                     <hi>1ſt</hi> Month, 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>A ſhort Teſtimony against that Spirit of Diviſion, that gave forth</hi> W. R<hi>'s Book, ſtiled,</hi> The Chriſtian Quaker diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed.</head>
            <p>WHereas there is a Libertine Spirit at work, very buſie to darken the Hearts of them that touch with it: I feel a neceſſity upon me, and that from the Lord, to bear my Teſtimony againſt it; and to caution all the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54975:56"/> tender ones not to meddle with it, leſt they be tinctured and hurt by it: for it is a ſubtil Spirit, and ſeeks, under fair pretences, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray Innocency, and ſome there are that are come to a loſs thereby, as woful Experience do daily ſhew; and therefore let it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how it is with thoſe that are alive to God: and how it is with thoſe that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of that Spirit, which gave forth <hi>W. R</hi>'s wicked Book, and thoſe that owns it, are they not in a dying condition, as to the pure Life of Jeſus? and let them whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings are not clear, take heed how they read in it, leſt they bring a Vail over them again they know not how: I may ſay, from a certain ſenſe, that it is a dark Spirit, and too many are groping therein; and that is the cauſe they do not ſee wherein the difference lyes: Oh that every ſuch a one would keep to that which did at firſt convince them, that they might have their underſtandings opened and kept open, that they might ſee how far they are on their Spiritual Journey, that this ſelf-ſeeking Spirit might not betray in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; for there are howling Deſerts, and dangerous Places, where this Spirit have lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corners, and creeps in at every turn, if the watch be not duly kept: And therefore let all take heed and beware of this deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, whatever it does pretend, it's no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the inwardly ravening Woolf, though cloathed outwardly like a Sheep, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54975:56"/> deceives the more: but the Lord will lay it open more and more for his own Seed ſake, that has long ſuffered: and the upright hearted who are true to God ſhall have great encouragement to travel on: but thoſe that are looking out are in great danger of being enſnared by this Spirit, which may make their Journey long and tedious, by muddlement of mind, and ſometimes go backwards, yet their way may be ſo hedged up that they cannot get quite back to <hi>Egypt</hi> again, but may die in the Wilderneſs, if they take not heed. Oh that all, while they have time, may come into obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Truth, and feed together in the Land of the Living, that in the feeling of Life we may ſing together as the Ranſomed of the Lord, dwelling with him (out of all ſtrife) in purity of Life, cemented together in the bounds of his Love, with our Affections fixed on things above.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To Friends in</hi> New England, <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>SAmuel Spicer,</hi> my Love ſalutes thee and thy dear Wife, and Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tilton,</hi> if yet alive, and the reſt of Friends
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54975:57"/> of your Meeting; and Friends at <hi>New York</hi> earneſtly deſiring your welfare in the Lord Jeſus, and breathing to the God of my Life, that above all things Truth may proſper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, and that Faith and Love and Peace and Life may be multiplied amongſt you, that the Work of the Day may go on, whatever you meet with to hinder: though the <hi>Philiſtine</hi> Spirit do ſtrive, and <hi>Amaleck</hi> lye by the way, yet good Encouragement have we, as faithful Soldiers enduring hardſhips, to travel on and follow our Captain fully; for his Reward is ſure, though it is through many Tryals obtained; yet when this momentary Pilgrimage is paſſed through, the greater weight of Glory will out-ballance all: and in the ſenſe of it, let our Hearts rejoyce; and our Souls magnifie that Power that has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and is able to preſerve unto the end: and that in and through it we may be ſtrong in the Lord Jeſus, and fitly furniſhed to every good Work, that we may never be weary of well doing, nor faint in our minds: though in this World we meet with many Troubles, yet we know him that is able to deliver out of them all; and if he feed with the Bread of Affliction, and the Water of Adverſity, yet bleſſed be his living Name, he teacheth our Souls to profit thereby; and we have cauſe to ſay in this Trying Day, as the three Children did in Ages paſt, We know that our God is able to deliver us, if he pleaſe; but if he will
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54975:57"/> not, we will ſtill truſt in him: for he has been with us in Six Troubles, and we have good cauſe to depend upon him, and to have confidence in him in the Seventh; for it is but a little while and Perſecution and Affliction ſhall come to an end: but the Word of Patience, that (preſerves in times of great temptation) abides for ever, and ſhall never have an end. Glory and Honour and Living Praiſes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and aſcribed unto the God of all our Mercies and Bleſſings, both Spiritual and Temporal, which we daily partake of from his fatherly hand: for he is an never-failing God, and of his loving-kindneſs there is no end: And unto the Protection of his Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power, which reaches over Sea and Land, do I commit you, with my own Soul, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth and for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Siſter in the unchangeable precious Truth, <hi>JOAN VOKINS.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> London,
<date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 3<hi>d of the 1st Month,</hi> 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:54975:58"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Friends of</hi> Crambrook <hi>in</hi> Kent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Love ſalutes you and the reſt of the Faithful in Chriſt Jeſus, who holds faſt their Integrity and retains their firſt Love: for ſuch are near and dear unto me, and often in my remembrance, whatever Exerciſes they undergo: and my Soul do often breath unto the God of my life, that we may be kept in a wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing frame, that if Tryals and Afflictions do abound, that his ſanctifying Power may ſuperabound, that as faithful Soldiers, we may endure hardſhips to the end; that in the end we may receive the greater weight of Glory, that may out ballance all the momentary Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that we meet with in this ſhort Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. O Glory to his Name, who is the Phyſician of Value, that can cure both Body and Soul; he is worthy to be truſted in, who never fails them whoſe confidence is in him, and all things are poſſible for his Power to do; therefore let our dependance be on it for ever, that we may feel it in all our undertakings, that we may have the benefit of it in the uſe of the Creatures, that his Bleſſing may be upon them, then it will go well with us, whatever may come. Thus the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus brings to paſs, for the honour of his own worthy Name, and the comfort of our
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54975:58"/> weak Bodies, and everlaſting benefit of our immortal Souls, is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true Friend in the unchangeable Truth, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>4th of the</hi> 9 <hi>Month,</hi> 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>For the Friends of</hi> Abingdon, <hi>Meeting in</hi> Berkſhire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear and well beloved Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF you will be delivered, then keep to Truth and that will ſet you free from Sin, and from Iniquity, and if you would wear the Everlaſting Crown: think not for to ſit down at eaſe, but follow the Lamb through the many Tribulations, that you may partake of his ſweet Conſolations: For the more Tryals and ſore Exerciſes do abound, the more the Love and Life of Jeſus will ſuper-abound unto all them that do believe in him and ſuffer with him, they ſhall aſſuredly reign with him, and be crowned with life, that are faithful unto death: and what is left upon Record we ſee fulfilling, that all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus muſt ſuffer, and the worſt Enemies are them of their own houſe: let them read that have experience, for they may underſtand me, and ſuch I truly ſimpathize with, in the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54975:59"/> patience and ſuffering of the Lamb: knowing that he and his Followers are deeply engaged in the ſpiritual warfare: and truly it is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and a bleſſed cauſe to be concerned in: and them that love any thing more than him, are not worthy to be concerned in his War, neither can ſuch partake of his Government and Peace, which ſhall never have end.</p>
            <p>Therefore them that go this ſpiritual war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, muſt not be entangled, but muſt follow their Captain through the many tribulations, bearing their faithful Teſtimonies, that their Garments may be made white, being waſhed in the Blood of the Lamb, that the precious adorning of his meek and quiet ſpirit, we may be covered with: that we may feel Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by him in our own hearts: then we need not fear what Man can do unto us: though all Men ſhould riſe up againſt us, yet if our God be for us, he can take our part, and plead our cauſe, and ſoon ſubdue our Enemies, if he pleaſes: but if he will not ſo do; yet we have cauſe to do as the Three Children did, to truſt in him however: for he knows what is moſt convenient for us, and he will cauſe all things to work together for our good: and if he gives the Bread of Adverſity, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Affliction, yet glory be to his worthy Name, he teaches us to profit thereby, and what he orders for us is ſtill for the beſt: and let us wait to feel his ſanctifying power to ſtrengthen us to follow him, which way ſoever
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54975:59"/> he leads, that we may love him above all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing things, and manifeſt our Love by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Commands: and one of his Commands which he gave unto all his, is (to watch) to be aware of their Souls Enemy, and to enjoy the ſweet benefit of their Souls Friend, which far exceeds the Friendſhip of all the World, and for the ſame we can turn our backs on the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the World, and do chuſe rather to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with the Lamb and his Followers, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon: for that would captivate our Souls: though we might have more favour from the wicked, and more eaſe to our bodies: but if hardſhip be our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that we muſt have a ſufficient ſhare therein: yet our reward is ſure, if we endure to the end. Glory and honour and praiſes unto the God of all our Mercies, and that for evermore; his bleſſed everlaſting reward will out-ballance all: therefore great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have we to wait upon the Lord Jeſus, for the renewing of our inward Man, that we may continue in well-doing, thoſe few days we have to come in this momentary Pilgrimage, that in the end God may be glorified, and our Souls (after all Trials and ſore Exerciſes are ended) may be everlaſtingly comforted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this you may ſee that I do not forget you, though ſo weakly in body, that I cannot viſit you; yet am with you in ſpirit, and as long as
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54975:60"/> we abide in the precious Truth, the Spirit of Truth writes us, as Epiſtles in one another's hearts, that cannot be forgotten: and in the ſame I dearly ſalute you, and bid you farewel in the Lord Jeſus, though in this World ye have many beſetments: yet unto his tender compaſſionate care I commit our Cauſe, and unto the Protection of his Almighty Power do I commend you, with my own Soul, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth and for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Siſter in the heavenly Relation, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Chawlow,</hi>
                  <date>1ſt of the 6th Month. 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Concerning her Journey into</hi> Ireland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BY this the bleſſed Truth, and them that love it may be cleared, that have unity with me in my Service: for I have a witneſs in every heart, that I may appeal unto; but them that take no heed to (the Spirit of God) the true witneſs in their own hearts, can have no experience of the work of it in others, and therefore no marvel if they wonder and periſh, as ſaid the Apoſtle: though they ſay daily and weekly, and year after year: it is their duty to love and fear and obey God with all
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54975:60"/> their hearts, with all their ſouls, and with all their ſtrength; yet ſo far are they from doing of it, that they are ready to caſt Aſperſions on thoſe that do: and though it's written in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that it is their Duties; yet they will not wait upon Jeſus to receive power to perform their Duties; and therefore they abide in unbelief and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not conſidering their time is ſhort, and the work of Sanctification is great. Oh how dangerous a thing will it be, to have ſuch a weighty work to do, when there is no time to do it! Well ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Work out your own ſalvation with fear and trembling:</hi> was that the way then; and is it become ridiculous now, that ſo many are ſo much averſe to it? Oh where are the Mockers and Scoffers, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of our Age? Who are hearing and reading the Scriptures without Underſtanding: Oh that they would take heed to that which reproves for evil; that their Underſtandings might be opened by it: for that is the Spirit that the holy Men were inſpired with, that gave forth the Scriptures: and until the hearts of People be turned to it, their underſtandings are ſo darkened, that they cannot ſee the ſtate of their own Souls; much leſs underſtand the holy Scripture: and therefore we need not care what ſuch can ſay or do againſt us, (who truly fear the Lord) for our reward is from him: and we have good cauſe to ſerve him, and ſeek to exalt his bleſſed Truth, by prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54975:61"/> it above all things: though Relations may be near and dear; yet to part with them, and natural Life and all, is but my reaſonable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, if my God require it; for I have found him a bountiful Maſter, and no reſpecter of Perſons: but them that truly fear him, and work righteouſneſs, do find acceptance with him: and that is more to a Remnant, then to find acceptance with all the Potentates of the World; for their favour will not procure peace with God: neither can thoſe live in God's holy heart-cleanſing fear: that offends him to pleaſe Man; and in vain will it be for any to hope to die in favour with God, and not live ſo in his fear, as not to offend him: and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the talk of loving the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and fearing him, yet there's none doth it, but them that leave off doing evil, and learn to do well; and ſuch keeps his holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, which are not grievous, but joyous to them, when the Lord doth enlarge their hearts, then can they run the way of his Commands with great delight: but while Man or Woman ſtandeth at a diſtance from that good Spirit that God hath, (in his tender love) given them to profit withal: they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſenſible of the Lord's enlarging their hearts, nor of his working in them, both to will and to do of his own good pleaſure: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all have regard to the work of God's Holy Spirit in their own hearts, that they may come to be ſenſible of the goodneſs of the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:54975:61"/> Lord, and the mighty works that he does for their Souls; and from a living experience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite others to come and taſt and ſee for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, how good our God is; for of a truth he is good unto his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that are of an upright heart in his ſight; and they can ſay of a truth, That one day in his Courts is better than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years in the Kings Palaces, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord is the fulneſs of our Soul's joy: and at his right hand is durable riches and pleaſures for evermore: and indeed it is weighty to conſider, how many are preferring the honour of Man, before the honour of God, and earthly riches before the heavenly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: And how eagerly do Mankind preſs after outward gain, and ſlightly eſteems the gain of godlineſs, though with content it is the greateſt gain of all.</p>
            <p>But my dear Friends, you that can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the Truth but for the Truth, I leave theſe lines with you, that the weak may not be turned out of the way, nor the feeble cauſed to ſtumble by any falſe Aſperſon, that the Devil through his Inſtruments may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to caſt upon me for the Truths ſake: For I have given no juſt cauſe to any to ſpeak evil of me; but if any ſhould take occaſion to ſpeak evil of the Precious Truth, becauſe of my ſerving it, let them know, that for this cauſe it was made known unto me, that I might truly ſerve it and not my ſelf; and if they that are Carnally minded would do ſo,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54975:62"/> they would then indeed know, that to be Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded is Death, but to be Spiritual mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is Life, and Peace, and true Contentment. And this I write as one that has had a woful experience of the enmity that lodges in the carnal mind, and a good experience and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge that redownds to the Souls of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Minded, and do earneſtly deſire that thoſe that are carnal and ſold under Sin, (as the Apoſtle ſaid) may turn unto that which is to ſay the enmity; for it is night unto every one: its the Word of the Lord which is the Sword of his Spirit, and as a Hammer to break down the partition-wall of Sin, which ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the Soul from the preſence of the Lord; and it muſt be known ſo to be, before Men can be fit to receive the things of God: and thus may People come to ſee between things that differ and not call good evil, and evil good, and put darkneſs for light, and light for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as too many do, by which the Lord hath been and is greatly provoked, and his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Truth vilified, and his Children daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached as evil doers, and that by all ſorts and Sects: it is now as it was in the days paſt, among the twelve Diſciples there was one <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> but he did not defile the reſt; but he went to the High-Prieſts and Rulers, and ſo ſided with them, that loved not the appearance of Jeſus: and ſo do theſe now that loves not his ſpiritual appearance, and can no more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the work of his Power in his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54975:62"/> than they could that ſaid, they were <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, when Chriſt told them plainly, that they were of their Father the Devil, and his works they were a doing, though they were very high in the World's eſteem (at that time) and he very low in theirs: and he told them the truth, and they hated him; and we have read what became of them, and of <hi>Judas,</hi> when he could not find Repentance, though he ſought for it. O therefore let the harms of thoſe, make all the diſobedient and gainſayers beware in time, and ſeek to honour God by their ſubjection to the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, who is come to ſave his People from their ſins, by his ſpiritual appearance in their hearts, that their Souls may have the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sentence pronounced at laſt by the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge, Well done good and faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, enter into the Joy which is prepared for all them that believes in Chriſt, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers with him, while on the Stage of this World, for theirs is the bleſſed Reward in the World that is to come; and they that ſuffer with him here, ſhall reign with him for ever. And in a living ſenſe of his Almighty Power that hath been already manifeſted is my heart encouraged to go on in his Service, not look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at weakneſs, or any outward thing that might by Natural Reaſon hinder: for who ſo poor, who ſo ſimple, who ſo weak, who ſo unworthy as I? Surely the Lord God of Love is manifeſting his Almighty Power in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Veſſels, that it may be the more
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54975:63"/> magnified; and let all that takes up the daily Croſs, and follows Jeſus, magnifie his Power; for unto ſuch it is daily manifeſted, to ſupply all their needs, and thereunto do I commit all for ever and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written by one that breathes for the proſperity of</hi> Sion, <hi>and deſires the welfare of all People,</hi>
                  <date>27. <hi>of the fifth Month,</hi> 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To Friends in</hi> Antegua <hi>and</hi> Nevice-Iſlands <hi>in the</hi> Weſt-Indies.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends in the Heavenly Relation, which is nearer than that of Blood, in which the God of all our Mercies keep us near unto himſelf, and one unto another, that as he renews his Mercies, we may renew our Obedience unto him, and our love one to another, that while we remain here we may breath one for another, that we may be refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, though outwardly far aſunder; that as Children of one Father we may feed together at one Table, and be nouriſhed with the Feaſt of fat things, that our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath provided for his ſincere ones, unto whom his love hath been ſo largely extended, as to preſerve in dangers deep, and made his wonders known, even unto a poor deſpiſed remnant, that he hath daily provided for, Glory to his worthy Name, and magnified be
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54975:63"/> that Almighty Power, that hath been ſo large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted in all our troubles, and helped us when we could not help our ſelves, and had none to help. Oh, how hath it wrought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances many, unexpectedly! Surely we have cauſe to truſt in it, and to depend upon it; for I have cauſe to ſay to the honour of it, there is nothing too hard for it to do; I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, and ſaw its mighty works to admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and it is daily marvellous in my eye; for it is ſtrength in the midſt of my great weakneſs, and a preſent help in times of my great need, and in the bleſſed enjoyment thereof I am ſweetly encouraged to go on in my place of Service, though in much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Body and outward Affliction: yet by this you may know that ſince Friends Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in <hi>England</hi> ceaſed, there was way made for my coming to <hi>Ireland;</hi> I had gone ſooner, but Sufferings were ſo great, that I could not leave Friends while it was ſo, and as ſoon as ever Friends came out of Priſons I came for <hi>Ireland,</hi> before I could get ſtrength over my long weakneſs; but leaſt I ſhould not live to come, I came forth in great weakneſs, becauſe it remained with me to come, and I have had a good experience of the tender dealing of the righteous God, who never required me to do any thing, but he gave me of his never-failing Power to perform it, and in the ſtrength thereof I Travel on in my Heavenlyh Progreſs, wherein the Lord God of all our Comforts and Conſolations preſerve us all unto the end,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:54975:64"/> whatever we have yet to meet with, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may be able to ſeparate us from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of our Heavenly Father's love, nor the ſeaſonedneſs of his heart-cleanſing fear, nor the refreſhings of his daily ſupplies of Soul-nouriſhing Life, and ſupporting Power, but through the feeling of the ſame, we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our watchfulneſs, and faithfulneſs, and continuation in well-doing, for he is a never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failing God, and from him all good proceeds, and therefore worthy to be waited upon all the days of our appointed time; for praiſes to the Name of Jeſus, we have good cauſe to wait, and not to be weary: for certain it is that he accepts of ſincere waiting, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news the inward ſtrength of them that truly waits, and diligently obſerves the dictates of the right Spirit, and joyns not with any thing that is wrong, theſe receive ability to do that which is right in the ſight of God, and in and through Chriſt Jeſus, ſuch comes to partake of the daily renewings of Life; whereby the heads of a Remnant have been born up in great Tryals, and ſore and various Exerciſes. Glory and Honour be unto our God, through his Son Chriſt Jeſus our Saviour, for he hath ſaved us when much evil hath been intended againſt us, and hath filled our Cups, and cauſed them to overflow; praiſed, and honoured, and renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be his Holy Name, for it is worthy, and that for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. V.</signed>
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>7th</hi> Month, 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:54975:64"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Women's Meeting in the Vale of</hi> White Horſe <hi>in</hi> Berks.</head>
            <p>DEar and well beloved Siſters, whom I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forget, but in that love that reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth over Sea and Land, do my Soul dearly ſalute you, hoping that the pure mind will be ſtirred up in every one of you, to conſider the matchleſs Mercies of our tender God, which I do here put you in remembrance of. Oh how hath he manifeſted his Almighty Power when we have been together in our Women's Meetings, and how have we been relieved and born up over all Oppoſitions, both inwardly and outwardly, and in the Goſpel-light have ſeen the great goodneſs of the Lord, and with the Goſpel-power been ſtrengthened when we were very weak, and ſupported when we were very needy? Hath not our Heavenly Father's love been ſufficient to engage our hearts to faithfulneſs? Oh that it may be as an Obligation to every one of us, to keep to the Goſpel-light, and to live the Goſpel-life, and to love the Goſpel-order, for our God is a God of Order, and he affords precious Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to wait upon him, and if we abide in a good ſenſe of his love, we ſhall not forget our times and hours to wait for the ſeaſons of the Lord; for they are ſo ſweet to the thirſty Soul, that it cannot be ſatisfied without them, and therefore many times thinks it long ere the Meeting-day come, that it might be repleniſhed
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54975:65"/> with the vertue of Chriſt Jeſus the Head, and ſtrengthened with the reſt of the Members: for as we truly gather in his Name (praiſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) he hath made us partakers of his Divine Nature: Oh how hath he bedewed our Souls, and cauſed our Cups to overflow, when the ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of his Eternal Power hath been felt among us to rebuke the Enemy, and keep him back, that would have hindred us from ſerving the precious Truth, and prevented us of the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Women's-Meeting: Oh that we may now take heed that we give him no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, by ſlighting the Mercies of our tender God, or neglecting of our Duties, but that in the remembrance of his tender Mercies and Fatherly Love we may double our diligence in our places of Service, that our God may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, feared, and obeyed by us all, that we may receive the bleſſed and ſure Reward in the end, when time here as to us ſhall be no more, and be in ſafety from all harms for ever and for evermore. So be it, ſaith the Soul of your dear Siſter in that which is ſtrength to the weak, and help to the helpleſs, that Sea nor Land cannot ſeparate,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joan Vokins.</signed>
               <dateline>From the County of <hi>Wexford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <date>the 26 of the ſeventh Month, 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:54975:65"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>SO dear hearts by this you may know that my tender God is ſtill exceeding good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and manifeſts his great Power, and it is admirable in my eyes, that I am yet alive, to tell of his wondrous works: but bleſſed be his worthy Name, he preſerves me by his Almighty Power, and in his tender love provides for me. Since I gave up all, he is more to me than all, Glory to his Name, and magnified be his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving and delivering Power; my Soul hath every day cauſe to ſay, for he hath done great and wonderful things for my Soul and weak Body, elſe I had not been alive at this day; but ſtill am I an object of his tender pity, and do hope ſo I ſhall be the remainder of my little time a Monument to his Praiſe. Many ſenſible Friends here are tendered in the ſenſe of God's love when they ſee me travel in ſo much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and I hope that you and I ſhall praiſe his Name together, and magnifie his Eternal Power (though in Perſon far aſunder) for it is worthy to be magnified, as it hath been manifeſted; for if that had failed, we had failed; but becauſe that lives, our Souls live to ſpeak well of the Name of our God, who is above all Gods, and there is none like unto him: it is honour to us ſufficient to ſerve him, for his Reward is ſure, and bleſſed be his worthy Name, he makes me a partaker daily of the gain of Godlineſs with contentment, which is a continual Feaſt.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Siſter in my meaſure, <hi>J. V.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:54975:66"/>
            <head>To her Children.</head>
            <p>AFter my dear Love to my Husband, This is to ſignifie my tender Love to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Truth, by my Motherly Care for my Children, that whether I live or die, you may be careful and take heed that you do not ſtain the Teſtimony of Truth, that you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by wearing of Needleſs Things, and following the World's Faſhions, in your Cloathing and Attire, but remember how I have bred you up: and conſider what manner of perſons you ought to be, now you are come to years of underſtanding, that you may not grieve the Spirit of the Lord, nor Me, nor any of his dear Children: but that you may walk as becomes the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you may be good Examples to others, and Patterns of Plainneſs and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs in your Converſations among all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; then will the Bleſſing of the Lord attend you, and it will be well with you in this World, and in that which is to come: then ſhall God be honoured, and my Soul with yours, and with the Souls of all his tender ones that deſires the ſame be comforted, and Truth promoted over all; and then you will have cauſe to ſay with me, That its Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy far tranſcends all that the World can afford, and will endure when that ſhall paſs away. And therefore forget not the Spirit of it in your Hearts, but take good heed unto it at
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54975:66"/> your Down-lying, and at your Up-riſing, that you with me may have the benefit of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Lord, who ſaid, <hi>he would be with his children at their down-lying, and commune with them at their up-riſing;</hi> and in this the day of his great love, he is nigh unto his Children, and delights in them that abides in a watching and a waiting frame, and takes councel of his Divine Spirit: <hi>But woe unto them, that takes councel, but not of me, ſaith the righteous God, and cover with a covering, but not of my ſpirit.</hi> And, dear Hearts, the day is come that all falſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings will be found too ſhort and too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to hide from the Wrath of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and them that are truly the Children of the Lord ſhall be covered under the Wing of his Eternal Power, from the Jaw of the ſtrong Deſtroyer, though he may caſt in Floods of Temptations, and may try by Subtilty to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray Innocency: yet, dear Hearts, look not at that, leſt your Faith ſhould fail, but look unto the Almighty Power of God, and wait to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and believe in it, and keep to the meaſure already received, that will make way for you to eſcape the Temptations, when you cannot help your ſelves, and have no other to depend upon. Oh then how have he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for me, and manifeſted his preſerving and delivering Power: Oh let your Souls with mine, magnifie it, for is it worthy, and that for evermore.</p>
            <p>Truth is the ſame here as in <hi>England,</hi> and Friends do not ſuffer the World's Faſhions to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54975:67"/> be followed, for both Men and Women here do go plain in their Apparel, according to Truth, in a comely manner; the Women do not attire their Heads, ſetting their Clothes aloft, imitating the World's Faſhions, wearing any needleſs things, nor in a needleſs manner: And ſome publick Friends from hence, are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>England</hi> in the ſervice of Truth, and more to go, and they will be grieved to ſee Friends Children ſtain the Truth, by attiring themſelves not in modeſt Apparel, and it would alſo be a great grief to me, if my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould be ſome of them. And therefore look to it, I charge you, in God's holy fear, that you may be warned and eſcape the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that do attend Youth, and be preſerved out of all the Snares of the Evil One, for they are many: And by this you may ſee, that I do remember you; and the breathing of my Soul is daily for you, and for all my Relations; and to them at <hi>Farringdon</hi> and <hi>Charney</hi> and <hi>Gooſey,</hi> and all the reſt of Friends there-abouts, mind my Love to them all as opportunity is, and let them know, that the Lord God of my Life and the length of my Days, is ſtill exceeding good unto me, and enables me by his Power to do his Service, and bleſſed be his holy Name, his precious Reward is with me, and that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes my Soul to rejoyce, and makes my Heart more glad, than the greateſt increaſe of all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things: Oh that it may be ſo with you, that your delight may be to ſerve him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your meaſures, that you may clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54975:67"/> ſee (by the bright ſhining of the Light) the vanity and folly of needleſs things in Apparel, and to lean after the World's vain unſetled Faſhions, is ſo far from being comely or an Ornament to any profeſſing Truth, that it is great cauſe of ſhame for any ſuch to wear it: and I am certain, that if you keep to the Gift of Chriſt's Spirit, that is given you to teach you to profit, and to lead you into all truth and plainneſs) I ſay, that I am ſure that if you hearken to the Spirit of Chriſt in your own Hearts, that then theſe needleſs things afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, and fooliſh Faſhions of the World will become a burden to you, as they are to me, and then you would be ſoon weary of them, and of all that is needleſs; round Attire upon the Head, ſet up aloft, nor long Ears to Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Dreſſings: I deſire, that the Lord may lay it home to your conſideration. And you may alſo hereby know, that I have had not one well Day nor Night ſince I came here; but I am not worſe than I was at home. I have travelled Three hundred Miles and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in this Nation of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and am now going for the <hi>North:</hi> I have been often very like for death, but have not lain by it yet, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord.</p>
            <p>I am uncertain when I ſhall be clear to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>return, but I intend to go no further than I have a neceſſity, becauſe of the weakneſs of my Body, and the Winter drawing on, it's hard for me to travel; but the Lord is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good unto me, beyond what I am able to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54975:68"/> expreſs. My dear love to all Relations and Friends. I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your dear Mother, <hi>J. V.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Dublin,
<date>18. 9 Mo. 86.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>An Epiſtle to Friends.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the Covenant of Life, unto whom the Lord in his unſpeakable love hath done ſo bountifully by, as to reveal his Son in us, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting our Souls when in a loſt condition and could find no comfort: Oh let his Mercies ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgotten, and the conſideration of his tender dealing abide with us: and let the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newings of his tender Mercies, both Spiritual and Temporal, give us freſh occaſions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our obedience; for if we abide in the conſideration of his love, we cannot but be tendered in the ſenſe of the ſame, and brought thereby into true ſubjection to the ſanctifying Power, by which we have been and are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, notwithſtanding all the dangers that hath or do attend: Oh the Excellency of the Power! it is ſo precious unto a Remnant, that we have continual cauſe to glorifie our heavenly Father, with all, and over all, for he is worthy; and if it be with Life and all, it's but our reaſonable ſervice; and thoſe that will ſave that alive that is to die, do thereby deprive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emſelves of Life eternal: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54975:68"/> we have all need to dwell low in the ſelf-denying Spirit, and the daily Croſs, that we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſtill enjoy the convincing Power, that we may travel on in our heavenly Progreſs with Valour and Courage, thoſe few days that are to come, in which we may expect many Troubles: But living Praiſes to the God of our Lives and Length of our Days, in him we find that Peace, that Man cannot give nor take from us, and in Chriſt Jeſus; our Life is hid from all that are in darkneſs, and under the ſhadow of death: and becauſe the Son of God lives, our Souls lives to praiſe his worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Name, his Eternal Power that has been manifeſted to tender our Hearts, and to bring us into ſubjection to ſo good a Maſter, daily nouriſhes and enriches our Souls with the reward of Life in our Boſoms, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes us to ſay with the Prophet, <hi>One day in his Courts is better than a thouſand elſewhere.</hi> And ſurely it is better to be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of God, than to dwell in the chiefeſt Palaces of the wicked: Oh how goodly are the Tents of <hi>Jacob,</hi> where we find ſafety in times of need; as we abide in Covenant with <hi>Jacob</hi>'s God, we have cauſe to rejoyce as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did, when the Rock that followed them was Chriſt Jeſus, the Rock of Ages, the ſure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Faithful, the Hiding-place, as the ſhadow of a mighty Rock in a weary Land, to ſhelter the weary Travellers by the way; the ſtreams of <hi>Shilo,</hi> that runs ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to comfort the comfortleſs, and to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54975:69"/> the weak, and relieve the thirſty Souls: Oh how ſweet are <hi>Shilo</hi>'s Brooks, where no Gally with Oars can paſs, where the Water of Life flows ſoftly, but ſweetly, without any thing that fleſh and blood can do, for that avails nothing in our heavenly Journey: and therefore to be had in no reputation, but to be daily denied, and the Croſs taken up, and following of Jeſus faithfully and fully towards the Crown, which is the bleſſed Recompence for us to look unto, that we may run the Race that is ſet before us in patience, that in the end we may obtain the Mark of the Prize of the High-Calling that is in Chriſt Jeſus, which is a Myſtery to thoſe that do not obey him, but a ſweet benefit to them that do obey his Call; for they are choſen ones, a peculiar People, zealous of good Works, glorifying our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father. And here we come to know that Scripture fulfilled, where it is ſaid, <hi>You ſhall call upon me in times of trouble and I will deliver, and you ſhall glorifie me.</hi> Oh that all the convinced ones, for whom I am ſo often concerned, would but conſider, that all that are amongſt us, might be of us, in glorifying God, by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Divine Requirings of his Love; for we all know ſufficient, but all do not obey; but yet the unfaithfulneſs of ſome do not make void the Reward of the Faithful, God forbid; but the Reward encourages them to invite all to taſte and ſee for themſelves how good the Lord is: for he is communicating of freſh ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of his tender Love, and Soul-refreſhing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:54975:69"/> Life, undeclarably unto them that fear him, and dare not offend him: and ſo loves him, as to keep his Commands; them he will make partakers of his precious Promiſes, for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed never to leave nor forſake his, and to be with them at their down-lying and up-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and at all times both day and night; and as we keep covenant with him, he will be with us, and we ſhall be with him that lives for ever to give Life to us, who waits upon him, and that we may have it more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, that we may live to his praiſe, though amongſt a crooked Generation, who do daily provoke the righteous God; ſurely the crying ſins of the ungodly have long cryed for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance in the ears of the mighty God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and his juſt Judgments will ſuddenly find them out: and then if <hi>Daniel, Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> were there, they ſhall deliver none but their own Souls: And therefore we have cauſe to be concerned as <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> that we may be Preachers of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in our Lives and Converſations, that as the wicked do diſhonour and grieve the Lord, we may be the more careful to honour and glorifie him, by bringing forth much Fruit, for his delight is in ſuch, and if we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in Chriſt Jeſus, the true Vine, then ſhall we be fruitful in every good Work; for he is the Root from whence we receive Vertue, elſe we ſhould wither and ſoon decay: but bleſſed be the Root from whence we receive Sap and Daily Relief: Oh that it may lye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54975:70"/> upon our Branches, that we may bring forth Fruit in due ſeaſon, and bloſſom as the Roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> and grow as the Lilly of the Vally, yielding a good ſavour in our words and actions, that whether together or aſunder, we may be one anothers joy and crown of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in the Lord Jeſus, in whom our freſh Springs are, who is the Fountain of all our Mercies, whoſe Streams makes glad his whole City, who relieves and repleniſhes our Souls, and gives us many fruitful Seaſons, and makes our Souls partakers of the early and latter Rain, and of his eternal Spirit, wherein is the Bond of Peace, in which the Lord God of all our Mercies, keep us all neer unto himſelf, and one unto another, that through the enjoyment of the ſame, we may magnifie his eternal Power, and Praiſe his moſt holy Name, for it is worthy to be honoured and renowned over all, and that for ever more, <hi>Amen,</hi> ſaith the Soul of your dear Siſter, in that which reaches over Sea and Land,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joan Vokins.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written at</hi> Droghedah <hi>in</hi> Ireland, <hi>the</hi>
                  <date>27. 9 Mo 86.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Friends here are well, and in the enjoyment of Peace and Plenty, bleſſed be the Lord, and Meetings large for the moſt part, and Friends unanimouſly concerned in the Service of Truth, as in the beginning, and keep their Zeal for Truth, and delights to live in it.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:54975:70"/>
            <head>Here follows a Paper that was printed in 1687, Entituled, <hi>A Tender Invitation unto all thoſe that want Peace with God, by reaſon of the burden of Sin that keeps them from acceptance with the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and from an aſſurance of Salvation, though it be very deſirable to them.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OH it's the weary and heavy laden that he tenders reſt unto, and they that take heed to his good Spirit which is light, and leaves off that which it condemns, and follows its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, they obtain the way of Life, and he becomes their Shepherd, and they hear his Voice, and a Stranger they will not hear; but they follow him; and he feeds them with that which the Strangers to his Voice, and hireling Shepherds cannot attain unto, by all their arts or parts external; but it comes to be enjoyed by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, that gives Victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Sin, and therefore it's time for all People to conſider; and as the Apoſtle ſaid, To try and examine themſelves, whether they be in the true Faith or no; for there is no true Faith, but that which ſtands in the Almighty Power, and that gives Victory over the Powers of Darkneſs; and without this Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God; as it is left upon Record in the Scriptures of Truth: So all is to believe in the Son of God, who is the light of the World, and hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned every one that comes into the World, as ſaith the Scripture; and in the univerſal love
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:54975:71"/> of God, he gave his Son for a Light to enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the Gentiles, and to be Salvation unto the ends of the earth, and he died for all; and his Love ſo far extended unto all, both Male and Female, that he would have none to periſh, but that all by turning to his good Spirit, may be ſaved from all that the evil Spirit leads into, for whoſoever follows the leadings of the Spirit of Jeſus, who is given for a Leader of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he leads them in the Path of Righteouſneſs, and as they come to be Servants of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they come to be free from Sin; but its written in the Scriptures of Truth, that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Sin are free from Righteouſneſs, and they that commit Sin are of the Devil, for he is the Original of Sin; but Jeſus Chriſt is the Original of the pure and holy undefiled Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that keeps from the Evil of the World, which is Pride, Adultery, Lying, Cheating, and Idolatry, and Superſtition, and other Spots that thoſe are ſtained with, who are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him, that ſaid, I Wiſdom leads in the midſt of the Paths of Judgment, to cauſe them that love me to inherit Subſtance; there is much talking of loving him, but few incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to keep his Commands; and much talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his fear, but little ſtanding in awe, ſo as not to offend him: but ſo far are many from taking heed unto the meaſure of his Spirit of Light, as he hath placed in their Hearts, that they do not know it leading them to the heart-cleanſing fear; For if they did, how could they plead for Sin, ſo long as they remain in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:54975:71"/> theſe Bodies; whereas it hath been ſaid by the Spirit of the Lord, and left upon Scripture Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that the fear of the Lord, is as a Fountain of Life, to depart from the Snares of Death: and the beginning of the true Wiſdom, and a good Underſtanding, have all they that follow after it, for they depart from iniquity; and it cleanſes the heart, and keeps it clean, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Teſtimonies the Scriptures bears Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of; and therefore unto it I recommend all People, that all may have the priviledge of it, that their Hearts may be cleanſed; for it is well known, there is no Repentance in the Grave, but as Death leaves, righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will find: and therefore let the long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and patience of the Lord lead to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſuch a Repentance that needs no repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, a changing of the heart, abſtaining and retraining from every appearance of evil: this is that which the Lord hath long waited for, and doth yet wait to be good and gracious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thoſe that confeſs and forſake their evil thoughts, words and works, and they ſhall ſurely find Mercy with him, and be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him, and feel acceptance with him, and know the work of his ſanctifying power, to ſanctifie throughout in Body, Soul, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that the works of ſanctification may not be to do when the Meſſenger of Death will not be denied, for then it will be too late to work out our ſalvation with fear and trembling: and therefore it would be good for all to conſider, how good the Lord is, in that he hath conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:54975:72"/> the frailty of all fleſh, and hath given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every one a meaſure of his good Spirit, to help our Infirmities, and to teach us: But if we neglect this Gift of God, we ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable in the Day of Account, and he will be clear of us all; and therefore let all be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to hear the Word of Reconciliation, that the work thereof may be experienced, for it begets again unto God, thoſe that were afar off, and when the work of Regeneration is witneſſed, and the Birth of the Water of Life, and Spirit of Jeſus; then the new Creature that avails with God, comes to be in unity and peace with him, and then the Spirit of Jeſus bears witneſs to the Spirits of ſuch, that they are the Children of the Lord, but except a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born again, there can be no entring into the Kingdom; for the firſt Birth cannot enter into the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s Nature, all are dead, but they that are begotten again by the Word of God's power, as the Scripture teſtifies, they come to be changed into the Nature of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven, the quickning Spirit, in him all ſuch are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, and as they live in his fear, and do not grieve his Spirit, their ſufficiency is in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted Word of his Grace that is able to ſave, and in the ſame do witneſs preſervation, as in the days of old; it is the ſame that <hi>David</hi> hid in his heart, that he might not ſin againſt the Lord, and it was as a Lanthorn unto his feet, and a light unto his paths: And ſo it is now, bleſſed be the Name of the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:54975:72"/> Lord, unto them that are truly watchful in it; but thoſe that are obeying the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, breaks the Command of Chriſt Jeſus; and it's left upon Scripture-Record, that he did not ſay only unto one, but unto all, watch; and ſurely it is as needful as ever for us to keep a narrow watch, and that in the Light; for our Souls Enemy works always in the dark, and except we keep a continual watch over our hearts, in that which doth diſcover his Snares, we cannot eſcape: and ſo let all that have any ſenſe, that it is their Duty to wait upon the Lord; be careful to keep the Command of watchfulneſs, that the Enemy, nor any of his Inſtruments, do not prevent from waiting in ſtilneſs upon the Lord, for he doth renew the ſtrength of them that do truly wait upon him, and the Lord by his Servant hath ſaid, <hi>That they ſhall run and not be weary, and walk and not faint;</hi> and now he is fulfilling the Scripture, wherein it is ſaid, <hi>The children of the Lord ſhall be taught of the Lord, and they ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, and great ſhall be their peace.</hi> Oh let all that want it hearken unto the true Shepherd of the little Flock, for whom the Kingdom is prepared, who encourages them, and bids them fear not, tho' the Wolfiſh deſtroyer is nigh unto them; yet he is the Overſeer, and in all Tryals and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes he is their preſervation; and them that have been exerciſed deeply, and tryed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they can tell of his wonderful works, and have cauſe to ſpeak well of his moſt worthy Name, and to invite others to come and taſte
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:54975:73"/> and ſee for themſelves, how good the Lord is, in that he gives all a time of tender Viſitation. Oh! that all People would but conſider it before it be too late, that while the good Spirit of Light is ſtriving, their hearts may be affected with it, and joyned to it, for it will not always ſtrive; and therefore let ſuch as could not come into Obedience becauſe of Sufferings, now conſider how good the Lord is, in that he hath calmed the ſtorms of Perſecution, and opened a door for ſuch as are convinced to come into Obedience; let them now perform what they promiſed to the Lord, when they were looking to ſee what the Lord would do with his poor deſpiſed People (called <hi>Quakers)</hi> for, ſaid they, it is the Truth that they ſuffer for, but we cannot ſuffer for it; the Sufferings is too hard for us to bear, elſe we ſhould own it. Oh! let all ſuch truly conſider the wonderful love of God, his tender mercy may not be diſregarded, nor his great love under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued, but let every ſuch a one double their diligence, and make no delays, for delays in this weighty concern are very dangerous; for who knows how little time they have to come, or what it may bring forth; therefore that the preſent time be not ill ſpent, <hi>but while it is to day, if any will hear his voice, let them not harden their hearts, as it was in the day of provocation:</hi> For many are the invitations of the great love of God, and if it be ſlighted, he will certainly with-hold his Mercies; and therefore we have great need to embrace his love, that we may
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:54975:73"/> not provoke him to wrath, for he is juſt, and will render unto all people according to their doings.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joan Vokins.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Weſt-Chawlow,</hi>
                  <date>14 of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> third Month, 168<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Teſtimon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> work of God's Power.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe of the marvellous love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, I cannot conceal my Teſtimony for the wonderful work of his Eternal Power that hath been admirably manifeſted in my poor Soul and weak frail Body, and if I ſhould not leave a ſhort Teſtimony of it to Poſterity, I ſhould be very ungrateful; and I pray God that the ſin of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude may not be laid heavy on any of us profeſſing Truth, when the Meſſenger of Death calls, but that while we live we may live in ſubjection to his Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power, that when we die, we may ſeal our Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies thereunto in true ſubmiſſion, and receive the bleſſed reward of the faithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OH what tongue can declare, the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful loving kindneſs of the Lord, as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced by thoſe that obey his Commands; Surely that is the way to abide in his love, and his great love has been ſo largely manifeſted to me, that it has ingaged me ſo to love him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as to forſake the Worlds Glory, Cuſtoms, and Faſhions, Vanities, Elements, Traditions, and Superſtitions, and to take up my Daily-Croſs and follow Jeſus through the many Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations: But bleſſed be his worthy Name; he hath filled my cup with his ſweet conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and cauſed me to ſay, that one day in his
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:54975:74"/> Courts, is better then a thouſand elſewhere; and I had rather be a door keeper in the houſe of my God, then to dwell in the pleaſanteſt palace of the Wicked: For until I through ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy, had unity with Jeſus in his divine Spirit of Light, my Soul could have no true ſatisfaction, though never ſo ſelf-righteous, but when the heart-ſearching Light made manifeſt my condition, my heart was ſo affected with it, that I ſtill deſired the operation of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it; and as I came to watch in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it, I became aware of the enemy, and through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus obtained a waiting ſtate; which could not be obtained by me, but as I felt the Almighty Power to rebuke the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til enemy that lies ſo nigh, but as we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to watch, we find great benefit by keeping that command. And magnified be that wonderful power that has preſerved in dangers deep, and difficulties many; there is nothing too hard for it to do, it has often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked the deſtroyer, and helped the helpleſs, and ſtrengthen the weak, and ſupported the needy, and as we have waited for it, we have been partakers of the ariſing of it, to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, when our Souls have been in a deſolate condition, when we cold not help our ſelves, nor had none to help us: Oh! how hath it wrought by Sea and Land, among falſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; it hath ſo ſignally preſerved and wrought deliverances many, ſomtimes by ways unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; ſurely its worthy to be truſted in, and depended upon, and magnified as it hath been
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:54975:74"/> manifeſted, my Soul hath cauſe to ſay to the Honour and Renown of it, for its perfect ſtrength hath been my ſupport in every great weakneſs, and in its ſtrength I have travelled many thouſands of Miles by Land, and many thouſand Leagues by Sea, through many and ſore exerciſes, both inwardly and outwardly, and it hath raiſed my Soul from Death, and my Body many times from the brink of the Grave: oh let it have the honour of its own Works, ſaith my Soul; for it is worthy, for it will make the ſtrong to bow, and the weak to be as <hi>David,</hi> and it is worthy to be extolled in a wonderful manner, for no heart can be too much affected with it, there is al-ſufficiency in it, to relieve the poor and to incourage the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: though there be much to be met with in our Heavenly prayers, yet here is a ſure defence in ſtormy times, wherein (glory unto it) I have found ſhelter, when many times in a weary condition by reaſon of exerciſe of Soul and Spirit, and weakneſs and pain of Body: Oh! how many hundred Miles have I travelled in this the Land of my Nativity, and thouſands elſewhere, in ſuch a condition, not having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny well Days in many Years together, but yet have good cauſe to ſay, (to the honour and renown of the ſanctifying power of the God of my life) bleſſed be the Lord Jeſus, his Rod and Staff has comforted me, and he is always with me, and I have cauſe to admire the tender deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Heavenly Father, for he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed me in the deep, and made his wonders
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:54975:75"/> known. And I have cauſe to ſpeak well of his worthy Name, for it hath been as oyntment powred into my poor wounded Soul, and it was alſo ſo much comfort and ſtrength to my weak body, that I can tenderly invite others, to come and taſt and ſee how good that name is that brings ſalvation, that thoſe that deſire for it, may obtain it; for as the heart comes to be bowed unto the powerful Name of Jeſus, and the Soul and Spirit comes to be gathered into a ſenſe of the great love of God; there will then be felt a neceſſity to ſerve and obey the God of all our Mercies. And this was with me when in great weakneſs, when temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations came in as a flood, and the buffetings of the enemy was ready to overcome; Oh Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and Magnified, and Renowned over all, be that Everlaſting Power, that wrought a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignment ſo effectually, and cauſed me to caſt my care upon him, that always careth for his children, who is the holy one, and dwelleth in the higheſt Heavens, and takes regard to them of low degree, for he has been more to me, then all that this World can produce, and hath fulfilled many precious Scriptures; and hath not been wanting as a tender Father, but his mercies of old, and the continuation of his favours, and the renewing of his tender deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have deeply obliged me to glorifie him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end, and in the end for evermore, for he is worthy, for he hath redeemed my Soul from out of the grave of Sin and Death; and now may I ſay to the praiſe, and honour, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:54975:75"/> renown of his powerful Name, that to live is Chriſt, and to die is ſo much gain, that my ſoul is deeply affected in a true Conſideration of the ſame; oh that my poſterity and friends for whom my ſoul hath ſo long breathed and travelled may be ſo concerned, that every one may be made partakers of the like precious faith with me, while on the ſtage of this World, that we may leave a faithful Teſtimony behind, that the generations to come may be induced thereby to fear and ſerve the Lord, for he is a ſure rewarder of all them that are diligent in ſo doing, not only in this Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but in that which is to come with Life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>ſting, World wtthout end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joan Vokins.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>This was written a few Months before her deceaſe, about the 1ſt Month, 1690.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> William Cooper <hi>and his Wife, dwelling in</hi> Weſt-Jerſey <hi>near</hi> Delaware-River <hi>not far from</hi> Burlington. <hi>Theſe are</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DEar and tender friends, <hi>William Cooper</hi> and <hi>M.</hi> my love in the unchangable Truth ſalutes you, and in the ſame I ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your welfare as my own, with all that holds faſt their integrity, and retains their firſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:54975:76"/> love, they are as near and dear unto me as ever, and my entire love truly reaches to them all, and ſo I deſire thou mayeſt let them know, if they have received my Letters and Epiſtles, for I have ſent ſeveral, but my kindſman dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the way, makes me queſtion whether what I ſent did ever come to any of your hands; for I ſent to you, and to <hi>S. Spicer,</hi> and to <hi>Lidia Wright</hi> (as was) and to her Husband, and to her Siſter <hi>Mary Andrews,</hi> and to ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al others in <hi>Penſilvania</hi> ſide, as well as on that ſide, and I ſhould be very glad to hear of your welfare in the Lord Jeſus, for that my ſoul ſtill travels as truly as when I was amongſt you. Oh that your faithfulneſs and living obedience may ingage our Heavenly Father to anſwer the breathing deſires of my Soul, for you in thoſe remote places; for I cannot forget you, but the cry often runs through me for your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and proſperity every way, and that the honour of Truth and the good one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother may be preferred far more then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, that our nearneſs and dearneſs unto our tender God, and one unto another may be felt and witneſſed, that we may praiſe his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Name, and magnifie his preſerving and delivering Power, for it hath been largely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, may a little remnant truly ſay, that has known the wonderful works of our God to admiration: Oh we have great cauſe to ſpeak well of his Name, and to remember his mercies of old, and to hold the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of his favours in great eſteem, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:54975:76"/> bleſſed be the Lord Jeſus, he hath not been wanting to us, but his renewed Mercies daily, are ſufficient to deeply ingage us to renew our faithfulneſs and obedience, that our heavenly Father may be pleaſed to continue and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his tender dealings towards us, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is yet to come, may never be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate us from the ſenſe of his love, or from the ſeaſonedneſs of his holy fear, or from that cementing life, that joyns us as Members unto Chriſt our Head, that if Tryals ſhould abound, we may all feel the Love and Life of Jeſus to ſuper-abound, that every bitter Cup that is yet to come may be ſweetened, and all hard things made eaſie, and we encouraged to travel on in our heavenly progreſs, keeping a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row watch in the precious Light, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waiting in the ſame, that we may be filled with heavenly Treaſure, for all other is very uncertain: And we here do meet with a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſhare of many and variable Exerciſes; neither do I expect, that you there do go free; but this is that I do deſire above all things, even your living growth in the precious Truth, and that you may indure to the end; for they are aſſuredly happy, and a bleſſed Reward is prepared for them: And in a living ſenſe of the ſame, the Lord God of our Lives keep us here, and you there, that our Breathings may be continued one for another, that we may be refreſhed one in another, and praiſe the God of Heaven and Earth together, (in his one Eternal Spirit) as with one Heart and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:54975:77"/> Soul, for he is worthy to be had in living re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and his pure power to be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified and renowned over all; and unto it I commit us all, for it is over all, and worthy to have the diſpoſing of us all; and with it I leave all, for there is nothing too hard for it to do, and it's worthy to be exalted over all Heaven and Earth, and that for evermore, ſaith the Soul of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>your loving Siſter in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Truth, Joan Vokins.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>28. 4 Mo. 90.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>HEre have been a very precious time of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bedewings at our General Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at this Seaſon, as at many other times, bleſſed be the God of Heaven and Earth, his Power has filled the Aſſemblies of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and the remembrance of you and other remote Iſlands is ſignified by Epiſtles that were Signed at our Womens Meetings, and ordered to be ſent to you, when opportunity preſents, that you may rejoyce with us, and joy in the God of your and our Salvation, in and through Chriſt Jeſus, who lives and abides to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us, his poor helpleſs ones, who have had no helper but him: Oh glory to his Name for ever, he has been with us in many Troubles, and gives us cauſe to believe he will be with us for ever: And unto his tender care do I commit all our States and Conditions; for freſh and ſutable Supplies comes from him,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:54975:77"/> the Fountain of all our Mercies, to whom be returned the Honour and the Glory over all, for he is worthy for evermore.</p>
               <p>The Lord my God, in his great goodneſs to me, (after a long time of weakneſs) has ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled me, by his Power, to come once more to this Yearly Meeting, to be refreſhed among his worthy ones, and could do no leſs then caſt my Mite into the Treaſury. And when the Epiſtle comes, as is directed, to <hi>West</hi> and <hi>East-Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> I intreat thee and thy Wife to let Copies be ſent to <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Long Iſland.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. V.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> Antegua <hi>and</hi> Nevice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>G. W.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DEar Friend, after the Salutation of my Dear Love, which truly reaches to thee, thy Wife and Friends, This is to let you know, That I cannot forget you in thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Iſlands, but have been often concerned for you in a Travel of Soul before the Lord, and now having this opportunity (after a long time of bodily Weakneſs) to viſit Friends at <hi>London,</hi> I can do no leſs than let you know, that, through tender Mercy, I am yet alive, to tell of the Goodneſs of the Lord, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Works of his Almighty Power, and to ſpeak well of his worthy Name, (for Glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:54975:78"/> and Honour and Praiſes thereunto) he is the ſame as ever, and his Mercies, and the continuation of his Favours, are never to be forgotten, and his renewed Goodneſs and Mercies, both Spiritual and Temporal, are daily ſufficient to engage us to renew our faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and obedience unto our tender God. Oh that thus it may be with all that he has been ſo good unto, as to bring near unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and one unto another, who were once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off from the Fellowſhip of the Saints in Light: but bleſſed be the Lord, who hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Light to ſhine in our Tabernacles, and ſhewed us the way that we ſhould walk in; and now Chriſt Jeſus is our Life and Salvation, and he fills our Cups with ſweet Conſolation; and as many as do walk in the Light have fellowſhip one with another, and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſes from all ſin, and purifies and fits the Earthen Veſſel for the Heavenly Treaſure; and the excellency of the power is of the Lord, and the Glory over all is his, and he is near unto them that ſeeks his Glory more than their outward Intereſt, and he will fill their Treaſuries with this heavenly Treaſure, and ſo as we follow him, we inherit ſubſtance, and have no more need to wander, as in the days paſt, after Husks and Shadows, but to keep to the Shepherd and Biſhop of our Souls; for bleſſed be his Name, he feeds us in the green Paſtures of Life, and cauſes us to lye down by the ſtill Waters, when the raging Sea foams out Mire and Dirt: Oh this is he
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:54975:78"/> that led <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the days of old, and never ſaid to the Seed of <hi>Jacob, Seek ye my Face in vain.</hi> And therefore, dear Friends, we have cauſe to ſay, to the praiſe of his holy Name, <hi>That goodly are the Tents of Jacob, and bleſſed is his dwelling place;</hi> for its within the munition of Rocks, where our Bread is ever ſure, and the Water of Life never fails, where the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry finds ſweet repoſe, and the thirſty are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, and where our Souls feed together, when our Bodies are far aſunder. So therein the Lord preſerve us and you unto the end, that he may have the Honour and our Souls the Benefit for evermore.</p>
            <p>And by this thou may'ſt know, that we have had a precious time here at <hi>London,</hi> at our Yearly Meeting, and many precious Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies have been born by Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to the Almighty Power of God, that have filled the Aſſemblies of his People: Oh how have the Heavenly Dew diſtilled upon our Branches, and brought forth Fruit that reaches unto you in theſe Iſlands, and I dearly deſire it may be pleaſant to your taſte, that we may be refreſhed one in another, and be one anothers joy and rejoycing in the Lord Jeſus, and that the Epiſtles of Love that were Signed here at our Yearly and Quarterly Meetings, may induce you to Write again, that you there, may have a correſpondency with Friends here, in the Work and Service, that our God hath called us unto, that Spiritual Fruits may be brought forth and abound in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:54975:79"/> for our heavenly Father who delights in thoſe that brings forth the Fruits of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and every Member that bringeth forth Fruit to his praiſe, he purges and waters with the Seaſons of his early and latter Rain, and cauſes them to bring forth Fruit more and more. And ſo the Dew of the Everlaſting Hills reſt upon you and us and upon all the Heritage of God every where, for evermore <hi>Amen,</hi> ſaith the Soul of </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>thy true Friend and Siſter, in that which reaches over Sea and Land, as length of time cannot wear out, <hi>JOAN VOKINS.</hi>
               </signed>

               <dateline>
                  <hi>At</hi> London.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I hope to hear from <hi>Nevice</hi> as opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to preſent, my Dear Love is to <hi>W. Fifill</hi>'s Widow, if yet alive, and to all the reſt of thoſe that are alive, that loves the Truth and lives in it, for they are very precious to me.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. V.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <argument>
               <p>This was written ſoon after the Yearly Meeting, 1690. about the end of the 4th or the beginning of the 5th Month, 1690.</p>
            </argument>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:54975:79"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of Books Printed for and Sold by</hi> Thomas Northcott.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOhn Burnyeat</hi>'s Works, <hi>Price</hi> 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. Keith</hi>'s Presbyterian and Independant, Viſible Churches, in <hi>New-England,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, brought to the Teſt, and examined, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Holy Scripture, Price</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Way to the <hi>City of God,</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His <hi>Fundamental Truths of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Price</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stephen Criſps</hi> Alarum ſounded in the Borders of Spiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> which ſhall be heard in <hi>Babylon, Prince</hi> 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Epiſtle concerning the Preſent and Succeeding Times, <hi>Price</hi> 2 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. Fox</hi> the Younger's Works, Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizabeth Bathurſts</hi> Truths Vindication, <hi>Price</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sam. Fiſher</hi>'s Works, <hi>Price</hi> 12 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Tomlinſon</hi>'s Innovations of Popery, <hi>Price</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Buds and Bloſſoms of Piety,</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. F</hi>'s ſeveral Treatiſes, worthy of every true Chriſtian's ſerious Conſideration, <hi>Price</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. Barclay</hi>'s Apology for the <hi>True Chriſtian Divinity,</hi> Price 4 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is now in the Preſs <hi>Robert Barclay</hi>'s Works, which will be a Book of 12 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
